absorption.
absorption.
Academia Sinica's April Intellectual Education Academy Lectures Begin
中央研究院4月份知识诲院演讲会开始
We ask Vice President Peng Xuming to host for us
我们请彭旭明副院长为我们主持
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
I'm glad that today is the time we miss again
很高兴今天又到我们知识想念的时间
The topic of today's speech
今天演讲的题目云山好荡
The Big Sea of ​​Clouds The Science of Clouds and Their Role in the Global Environment
雲海茫茫 雲的科學和他們在全球環境中的角色
We knew this topic was very knowledgeable and interesting
我們就知道這題目給得很有學問 很有意思
Then I think the summary of this speech is for your reference.
那我想這個演講的摘要就供大家參考
Especially if you read this summary after I've heard the speech
尤其等我聽完演講以後 你再讀讀這個摘要的話
will be very helpful
會很有心得
Then let me briefly introduce the speaker
那還是要跟將主講人簡單介紹一下
This Dr. Huang Baoguan graduated from Tainan No. 1 Middle School in 1967
這個黃寶冠博士是1967年在台南一中畢業
Then in 1971 take this break this meteorology
然後1971年拿到這個休息這個氣象學
It is now the Department of Atmospheric Sciences of National Taiwan University
現在變成就是現在的台大大氣科學系
Then he served in the military for two years
然後扶了兩年的兵役
That was the first year of military service for two years
那是第一年扶兩年兵役的
I look for him for a year and I only support one year of military service
我找他一年我只扶一年的兵役
In 1970, I fell to the United States in 1971
1970年我1971年就摔到美國去了
I just came to this UCLA to study for a Ph.D.
才到這個UCLA去攻讀博士
Then get a doctorate in seven or eight years
然後七八年拿到博士學位
in atmospheric physics
就在大氣物理方面
Then he worked as a postdoctoral fellow and part-time assistant professor at UCLA
然後在元校UCLA擔任博士後跟兼任的助理教授
From 1980 onwards in
到1980年以後開始在
This from the University of Wisconsin Medicine
Wisconsin大學的Medicine的這個
This branch served as the beginning of his academic career
這個分校擔任這個開始他的學術生涯
Become an associate professor in four years and a professor in four years
四年變成副教授再四年變成教授
Professor since 1988
1988年就是教授
Then from 1994 to 1997 served as the atmosphere
然後1994年到97年擔任的大氣
Dean of the Department of Marine Science
跟海洋科學系的系主任
Director of the Air Resources Management Program from 1998 to 2002
98年到2002年擔任大氣資源管理學程的主任
The beginning of the year January 1, 2013
今年年初2013年1月1號
Our Central Committee is very fortunate to fight back to be our hospital
我們中央很有幸的拼拿回來當本院的
Director of the Center for Environmental Change
環境變遷中心的主任
that in his academic career
那在他的學術生涯裡頭
Been in National Taiwan University
當過台灣大學
Massachusetts Institute of Technology, we call MIT
美國麻省理工我們叫MIT的
italy
義大利
University of Ferrara
菲拉拉大學
University of Mex, Germany
德國Mex大學
besides
還有
German
德國的
maple
麻普所
Institute of Chemistry
化學研究所的
science professor or visiting professor etc.
科學教授或者訪問教授等等
once obtained
曾經獲得
America's
美國的
Johnson's on it
上面有Johnson的
Distinguished Scholar Award
傑出學者獎
also received the German
也獲得德國的
Homber's
Homber的
this
這個
Senior Excellence Award
資深傑出獎
That
那
used to be his main research direction
曾經為他的主要研究方向
is atmospheric physics
是大氣物理
especially
尤其是
Microphysics of clouds and rain
雲雨的微物理
With the dynamic mechanism
跟動力機制
Past Chair of the American Meteorological Society Committee on Cloud Physics
曾經為美國氣象學會雲物理委員會的主席
The main and more important thing is that he has a Chinese version
主要更重要的他住有中文版的
cloud physics
雲物理學
and in
而且在
Enthusiastic about science
熱心科普
yes there are many
對有很多
popular science works
這個科普的著作
like heaven and earth
譬如天與地
from Newton Press
是牛頓出版社的
Top 10 Open Books of 1996
1996年的開卷十大好書
Then there is a book called moving tea
然後有一個一本書叫做動茶
is the culture of the world
是天下文化
It is the home of the first Wu Dayu Science Popularization Award
是第一屆吳大猶科普獎的家座
Home of the 2002 Jinling Awards
2002年的金陵獎的家座
And Wei Sung Dae-kyeom
還有維成大謙
by Classic Magazine
是由經典雜誌
The 2005 Jinling Award finalists and so on
2005年的金陵獎的入圍等等
So he is also very enthusiastic about this popular science.
所以他對這個科普也非常熱心
together we can have a good day
我們可以一起今天有很好的
this speech we all
這個演講我們大家
applaud him
鼓掌歡迎他
Thank you Vice President
謝謝副院長
Goodnight everybody
大家晚安
Just now the vice president did a lot
剛才副院長做了很多
too
太
It's an honor to introduce
太光榮了一點的介紹
not so honorable
沒有那麼光榮
but glad to have the opportunity tonight
不過很高興今天晚上有這個機會
let's chat
來跟大家聊一聊
I'm doing a major in one aspect of the research I'm doing
我在做的研究的一方面的專業
I mean the speech has to have a nice name
我是說這個演講總要取一個好聽一點的名字
If I talk about the science of clouds all at once
我如果一下子說雲的科學
Maybe everyone doesn't want to come
可能大家都不想來
But what did I say about clouds and mountains?
可是我說什麼雲山浩淡之類的
i tricked everyone
我把大家騙來
let's talk slowly
我們再慢慢慢慢講
When the dean of our society came here for an interview,
我們會院長在那時候我來這邊面談的時候
At that time I didn't know whether to come or not
那時候我還不知道要不要來
He told me about you this April
他就有跟我說你這個4月
He will come to us at the end of April to talk about this science in detail.
4月底要來我們這裡講這個科學詳細
so i thought about it
所以我想了一下
I didn't know whether to come or not
本來不知道要不要來
Later, I thought about it and said that I had promised others that I would come.
後來想想說已經答應人家說要來了
So if you don't come to this ring transformation center
所以如果不來這個環變中心的話
I can't seem to make sense
好像說不過去
I'm very happy to finish the show
我非常高興做完演來
I just came here for 4 months
我剛來滿4個月而已
everything is not very very familiar
一切都不是非常非常熟悉
What I want to report to you today is
今天要跟各位報告的是
something about voice
有關語音方面的一些
common sense mostly common sense
常識 多半是一些常識
Of course it will also mention some
那當然也會提到一些
We are more professional in the research part
我們比較專業一點的做研究的部分
Then my general speech is
那我一般演講就是
I don't like too much shock
我不太喜歡太震驚就是
so hope
所以希望呢
Needless to say we have to wait until all the speeches are over
不必說一定要等到全部演講完了以後
only ask if you have a question
你有問題才問
if you have something in the middle
你如果中途有什麼
small questions or relatively short
小的問題或者比較短的
hope to understand soon
希望馬上可以了解的
I feel free to ask
我覺得可以隨時提問一下
But if you compare the question
但是如果比較堂的問題
Of course we'll wait until it's all over
當然我們就等到全部講完以後
But if there is such a
但是如果有隨時有這種
small problem words
小問題的話
I think you are welcome to bring it up anytime
我覺得歡迎大家隨時提出來
OK
OK
Thanks
謝謝
it doesn't seem to move
這好像不動
yes call me yes
是撥我 對
This has
這個有
yes it's ok
有啦 可以啦
oh down ok
喔 倒了 OK
OK, thanks
好吧 謝謝
we start from that
我們從那個
not a science start
不是科學開始
so-called literature
所謂的文學
Or generally we are right
或者是一般我們對
This impression of the cloud is beginning to speak well
雲的這種印象開始講好了
But I'm in my Zhuzhu
不過我在我的卓柱裡面
in that insight
那個洞察裡面講說
People generally think that literature is not science
一般大家認為說文學好像不是科學
Actually a good writer
其實好的文學家
In fact, this kind of scientific observation has been done very carefully.
其實做了很仔細的這種科學觀察
articles he wrote
他寫的文章
to reach your heart
才能夠達到你的心裡面
that's my point of view
那是我的觀點
If everyone uses this mood in the future
如果以後大家用這種心情
go see some litterateurs
去看看一些文學家
books written by famous writers
出名的文學家寫的書
still
還是
or article you will find
還是文章 你會發覺
In fact, they observed very carefully
其實他們觀察得很仔細
But because he observes very carefully
但是因為他觀察非常仔細
What he writes will move your heart
他寫的東西才會拿動你的心
so there's science in it
所以其中有科學在裡面
It's not that literature means that you don't know science
不是說文學就要不懂科學
OK, what is our first impression of this cloud?
OK 我們首先對這個雲到底有什麼印象呢
in our usual words
我們平常的用詞裡面
A lot of Guanye Yun about this choice is very elegant
一大堆冠冶雲有關這個優選很飄逸
Or it is very advantageous between some hatred
或者很優勢一些嫌仇之間
We often use language called
我們常常用語言叫做
Flowing clouds and flowing water
行雲流水
On behalf of others, the writing style is very good
代表人家文筆寫得很好
Teacher, your article is well written
老師 你的文章寫得
For example, like the Controversy Exhibition in our area
比如說像我們在座地區所的造說展一樣
Flowing clouds and flowing water
行雲流水
that's the right word
那就是用對的字
The monk who seems to have nothing at all is called Yunshui monk
那個好像一點千半都沒有的和尚叫雲水和尚
So this is also a kind of wandering everywhere
所以這個也是一種那種到處流浪到處漂泊
no homeless kind
沒有無居無宿的那種
Then I just cite some examples here.
那我這邊隨便舉了一些例子
That's us, I think everyone probably
就是我們這 我想大家可能都
read these sentences
念過這些句子
In the description of the cloud in these sentences
這些句子裡面有關雲的描述裡面
What kind of yo-yo are they all using?
全部都是用什麼悠悠這種講法
Is that cloud Yoyo?
那雲是不是悠悠呢
Of course, we look at it from the eyes of ordinary people.
那當然用我們常人的眼光來看
indeed Yoyo
的確是悠悠
it just hangs there like there's nothing going on
它好像沒有什麼事情就掛在那裡
Sometimes it takes a long time to hang
有時候一掛就好久好久
Then it seems to be slightly fluttering with the wind
然後它好像又隨著風稍微可以飄飄
but i want to tell you
不過我要跟大家講說
that was a wrong impression
那個是錯誤的印象
Then you were deceived by the cloud
那你被雲騙了
In fact, the cloud is very busy
其實雲很忙
Of course, that's from a scientist's point of view.
當然那是以科學家的眼光在看
I'll explain to you later
我等一下會跟大家解釋
This shadow of Yin Yun
這個賢雲殘影
have this impression
有這種印象
A few years ago, I went to this to that Italy for a meeting
我前幾年在那個這個到那個義大利去開會
in that so-called
在那個所謂的
That Edrisie over there in the Adriatic Sea
那個亞德利亞海的那個愛德利斯伊那邊
I saw this cloud early in the morning before going to a meeting here
去開會之前那個一大早就看到這個雲在這裡
Come back at four or five in the afternoon
一到下午四五點回來
The same rain is still there
同樣那個雨還在那裡
wow that's really relaxing
哇那真的是很悠閒啊
That place seems to have just the right day and the weather is very good
那個地方好像那天剛好天氣也非常好
From this island, one can see that the cloud in the distance is
在這個島上一看就是那個遠遠的那個雲就是
Strange hanging all day
奇怪的掛了一整天
So if you just look at this phenomenon, you should think that the cloud is really leisurely.
所以你如果光看這種現象應該就那個雲真的是很悠閒
It's all right hanging there like that bum sweat
沒事好像那個流浪汗一樣就掛在那裡
But what?
不過呢
When I was going to talk about it, it was also an illusion cloud. You thought he was hanging there all the time.
我要講的時候那個也是假象雲你以為他一直掛在那裡
In fact, it's already different
其實早就已經不一樣了
As for why it is different
至於為什麼會不一樣呢
you will understand later
你接著會明了
But your leisure will be punished
不過你那個悠閒也會挨碼的
Some people also made this cloud
也有人把這個雲冒的
this one
這一位
This gentleman is called Laihu
這一位先生叫做來虎的
that's what he's talking about
他就是講這個
Thousands of Lines Looking Forward Rough Sky Hard Water Nagayama
千行望向 進荒空 硬水長山
Pian Fu Cong Unlimited Han Miao Ku Yi Bacteria
片復從 無限漢苗 枯一菌
Yoyo, virtuous place, do prayers
悠悠 賢處 做祈奉
He means that the cloud is in this
他是說這個雲在這種
no one sees over there
沒有人看到在那邊
The place no one cares about is over there
沒有人管的地方在那邊
change
變來變去
But some of that
可是呢 一些那個
Waterway, some seedlings
水道啦 一些那個苗
fucked to death
被乾的快要死掉了
he doesn't go to the rain
他也不去下雨
Still wandering over there
還在那邊賢逛
So this is scolding the cloud
所以這個是在罵雲的
some people don't understand
有人看不懂
Thought this was well done
以為這個是做得很好
so hang him there
所以把他掛在那裡
I don't know what this is
就不知道這個是
Actually a curse poem
其實是罵人的詩
Cloud of Hell Round Leaf Item
雲的地獄園頁項
That is to say, the cloud is ever-changing
就是說雲是千變萬化
We usually belong to the saying
我們平常屬於常常有句話
Baiyuncanggou
叫做白雲蒼狗
It means that the world is actually changing
就代表說人世其實這個變幻
very very big
非常非常的大
This source is from this
這個來源是從這個
from a poem by dufoe
杜福的一首詩裡面來的
It is "Heaven Fu Yin Fu White Clothes"
就是《天上福隱福白衣》
poems and songs change like dogs
詩曲改變如唱狗
so the sentence
所以這個句子
Condensed by us into Hakuin singing dog
被我們濃縮成白隱唱狗
meaning it gets very fast
意思就是它變得非常快
another one
另外一個
The same meaning is the same as the cloud circle of the world
世事雲圈邊也是一樣的意思
It's just that things in the world change
就是世界的事情變來變去
come and go
人世一下來走
So this world is clouded
所以這個世事雲圈邊
It also means that clouds come and go
同樣也代表雲變來變去
This is, of course, generally speaking
這個當然也是從一般來講
Observed cloud changes are very fast
觀測到雲變化是非常快
Usually if you like to watch the cloud
通常大家如果喜歡看雲的人
I myself have loved watching clouds since I was a child.
我自己從小就很喜歡看雲
So study the cloud
所以念上雲這一門
probably not wrong
大概也不冤枉
Many of you here may like to watch clouds
在座可能很多人很喜歡看雲
i have one thing to say
我有一點就是說
please don't look while driving
開車的時候拜託不要看
very dangerous
很危險
because it's fascinating
因為看得很入神
Suddenly found this problem out
突然發覺這個問題出來了
But one of the clouds is very special
可是雲的一個很特殊
That is to say, when you look at you, it is equal to
就是說你一邊看你等於
You just blink and it has become the same
你只要一眨眼 它已經變成一個樣子
Do you feel like a fish is growing
你覺得一個魚好像在長
then you might say take a break
那你也許說休息一下
Or someone just called you
或者人家剛好打那個電話給你
You spread it out for another 20 seconds
你再稍微散開了它20秒
That fish might disappear
那個魚說不定就不見了
very strange
很奇怪
So some people have been dreaming
所以有的人就一直在很納夢
that is to say the fish
就是說這個魚
How on earth is it possible to become so fast
到底是怎麼可能會變得那麼快
Then there is a
然後這邊有一個
there is a video
有一個video
A small movie can be
一個一個小電影的可以
You can see how the fish is changing
大家可以看一下那個魚在變的情況
oh
喔
can't come back
回不來
this is going to be moved above this
這個要移到這個上面
You can see the fish have formed
你可以看到魚有的形成
maybe i see this
可能是肚腑看到這個
This is like a dog
這個就像狗啦
like a cat or something
像貓啦什麼之類的
this is changing
這是變來變去
sometimes it seems like something out of nothing
那有時候好像無中生有
Sometimes it pops up out of nowhere
有時候突然從沒有地方突然冒出來
So this of course speeds up the time
所以這個當然是把時間加快
This is a kind of time lapse to tell the truth
這是一種說實的一種time lapse
honestly this movie
說實的這種影片
But I have to say so you can see
但是我有這樣講你才可以看到
It is said that the change of the cloud is indeed very fast.
說雲的改變的確是非常快的
and it turns into this
而且它一下變成這個
suddenly become like that
一下變成那樣子
so this is
所以這個就是
Why does it cause the so-called world cloud change
為什麼會造成所謂的世事雲全變
such an impression
這種一個印象
Then you see this cloud now
那你現在看到這個雲
Of course, it's mainly chicken clouds on sunny days
當然主要是晴天的雞雲
that under different weather conditions
那在不同的天氣狀況之下
Variations of various clouds
各種不同的雲的變化
Another way
又是另外一種一種一種樣子
OK
OK
So not just the kind of cloud itself
所以不只是雲的本身的那種
dynamic changes
動態的變化很大
Even clouds come in all shapes and sizes
甚至雲的形狀也有各式的
are various changes
是各樣不同的變化
like this cloud
比如說像這種雲
Everyone must have seen it
大家一定也看過
This kind of cloud is called cirrus cloud
這種雲呢就是所謂的捲雲
It's probably very, very long
它多半呢就是很長很長
so often this slightly acts like a hook
那常常這個稍微會像鉤子一樣
Westerners say this is like a horse's tail
西方人說這個像馬的尾巴一樣
that ponytail cloud
那種馬尾的雲
that's true
那的確呢
It's usually shaped like this
它的形狀通常就是像這種樣子
very long very
非常長非常
Often the entire sky is filled with a mass of these clouds
常常在整個天空部滿一大堆這種雲
That used to be in basic meteorology
那以前在基礎的氣象學裡面
Teachers often say that you see this kind of cloud
老師常常會說你看到這種雲呢
it means the weather may change
就代表說天氣可能會變
But sometimes I watched for a long time
不過有時候看了半天
The weather may not change
那個天氣也不見得會變
Weather, if you only look at clouds
天氣這個你如果只會看雲的話
This is not very accurate
這個不是很準的
That thing has changed a lot
那個東西變化實在太大了一點
But what about this cirrus cloud?
不過這個捲雲怎麼回事呢
Cirrus clouds are actually high-altitude clouds
捲雲其實就是高空的雲
it's very high
它非常高
usually very thin
通常也非常薄
What I mean by thin is thin
我所謂薄的意思是細薄的意思
But it's not thin in terms of thickness
但是以厚度來講它並不薄
its possible after a few kilometers
它有可能好幾公里後
I generally think that
我一般認為說
This seems to be within a few hundred meters.
這種好像應該是幾百公尺的範圍
Actually no
其實沒有
cirrus clouds may be several kilometers away
捲雲有可能好幾公里後
but it's thin
但是它很稀薄
so you can see right through it from the ground
所以你可以從地面一直看透它
so it looks like
所以它看起來
when the sun shines
被太陽一照的話
it's very very bright
它就非常非常的亮
Because it's mostly ice crystals
因為它主要是冰的結晶
so this kind of thing
所以這種東西
cirrus
就是捲雲
This is more familiar to everyone
這個是大家比較熟悉的
cirrus cloud
就是所謂的捲雲
Of course there are small and big cirrus clouds
捲雲當然有小的有大的
that movie we just had
我們剛才那個電影
That is called sunny cirrus
那個叫晴天捲雲
because it was sunny
因為那是晴天的時候
cirrus clouds
出現最常常有的這種捲雲
this one is bigger
這個就比較大
This is from that accountant
這個是在從那個會計的
founding out
創始外面派出去
This is what we call dense cirrus cloud
這個是我們叫密捲雲
because it grows a bit bigger
因為它長得比較大一點
Then you can see the shape
那你可以看到這個形狀
I think of when you eat
就想到你吃飯的時候
The kind that eats that cauliflower
吃那個花菜的那種
You see cauliflower, this is gene
你看到花菜,這個是基因
If you like Niu-Stopology and you see this thing, this one is convection
如果你喜歡牛停立學,你看到這個東西,這個是對流
Why convection? There is this relative movement between the air outside and the air inside
為什麼對流?外面空氣跟裡面的空氣有這種相對運動
So there are a lot here, if you look at them carefully, it looks like a small team bag
所以這邊很多,你如果仔細看了他們,好像小隊伍包一樣
keep moving
一直不停的在動
I saw it when I was a kid, I practiced this reservoir very early
我小時候就看到,我很早就練過這個儲池
This is Yun Zhongjun from Chuchi Nine Brothers
這個是儲池九哥裡面的一個叫雲中軍
This is one of the ancient cloud gods
這個是古代的雲神的一種
In his commentary, I just wanted to laugh when I saw it, Yun Zhongjun is Yunshen Fenglong
他的註解裡面,我看了就想笑,雲中軍就是雲神風龍
I believe that name is all about being there
我相信那個名字完全就是想搭那兒
You see this kind of gene, it really looks fat
你看到這種基因這種樣子,果然就是胖胖的樣子
Of course it's very windy
當然就是很風龍
He said another name is Ping Yi
他說另外一個名字叫做平易
This simplicity simply means to block things.
這個平易根本就是把東西擋住的意思
Of course, the cloud is blocking the sun
雲一多當然是把太陽擋住了
So this god's name is probably a bit artificial.
所以這個神的名字大概有點是人造的
This kind of cloud you often see this so-called achievement
這種雲你也常看到這個所謂的成績
You say like it's not full of the sky
你說像它不滿天空
But you can divide it piece by piece
可是它你又可以分出來一塊一塊
So this kind of cloud is also full
所以這種雲也滿長的
The other one is called a convective cloud
那另外一個叫做對流雲
Convective clouds are
對流雲這種就是
Usually its vertical scale is a bit larger than its horizontal scale
通常是它的垂直比它的水平尺度要大一點
So this is generally produced by convection
所以這個是一般來講是對流產生的
Then this is of course the cloudy weather in summer in Taiwan.
那這個當然就是我們台灣夏天這種雲多的是
And this kind of cloud you usually see
而且這種雲你通常看到的話
More likely means that there is a chance of rain often
多半代表常常有可能會下雨
Also this kind of cloud, since it is so thick, it means
也這種雲它既然那麼厚這代表
Some of his ascenders are very strong
他的上升器有的非常旺盛
Some ascenders are so strong
上升器有的这么旺盛
There is a high chance of rain
下雨的这种可能性就很大
But it's also a possibility
但是也就是可能性
If you say he will definitely rain
你如果说他是不是一定就下雨
Not always
那可不一定
sometimes he can't get down
他有时候下不来
But the so-called not coming down means not getting down to the ground
但是所谓下不来的就是说下不到地面
if you are in the rain
你如果在雨里面
then he will come down
那他一定会下
If you go back into the rain
你如果回到雨里面
There are many raindrops on that window
那个窗子上很多雨点
On that glass of this plane
在这个飞机的那个玻璃上面
you can see
你一定可以看到
There must be strong raindrops in this convective rain
这种对流雨里面一定有大力的雨滴
when a convective rain
当一个对流雨
Like when I grew up in a tall place just now
像刚才那种长大一个蛮高的地方的时候
This usually reaches a certain height
这个通常他到一定的高度
That height we call convective sinking
那个高度我们叫做对流沉顶
The lowest layer of the atmosphere on the ground
地面上这个大气层最低的这一层
We call it convective sinking
我们叫对流沉
Basically, he arrived at about 10 kilometers.
基本上大概他这一到差不多10公里左右
sometimes ten kilometers
有時候是十幾公里
onto that
到那個之上
another city
另外一個城
There is probably Stratocity over ten kilometers away.
那個十公里以上大概有平流城
Stratocity-like movement is difficult to penetrate
平流城一般的運動很難透過
So the general cloud goes to this convective city
所以一般的雲就到這個對流城
It's like there's an invisible glass blocking it
就好像有一個無形的玻璃一樣把它擋住
your convection basin to the top
你這個對流域到上面
its cloud won't go up
它的雲上不去
But it can always be opened from the side
可是它總可以從旁邊上開
So it has this kind of opening on both sides
所以它就有這種往兩旁上開的
So this so-called chicken cloud
所以這種所謂的雞雲
Chicken clouds are generally connected with the so-called lightning phenomenon
雞雲一般來講就跟所謂的雷電現象連在一起
Usually it produces lightning and thunder
一般它就產生閃電打雷
this phenomenon
這種現象
This is the so-called chicken cloud
這個就所謂的雞雲
Just now, it was probably the general impression we have of clouds.
剛才大概都是一般的我們對雲的這種印象
what is it like
大概是怎麼樣的
Let me see what the artist thinks about this cloud
我看看藝術家對這個雲的感想是怎麼樣的
this belt this
這個送帶的這個
A painter named Guo Xi
畫家一個叫郭希
Everyone, if you go to the Boyuan of the Forbidden City
各位如果到故宮伯苑
There are several very large paintings
有好幾幅很大很大的畫
He once wrote an article called "Linquan Gaozhi"
他曾經寫了一個文章叫《臨泉高智》
He narrates a lot in it
他裡面就敘述了很多
If you want to draw clouds, how should you draw them?
你如果要畫雲的話應該怎麼畫
Of course he mainly said
他當然主要是說
The clouds in spring should be like white cranes
春天的雲應該像白鶴一樣
The wind is blowing
下雲都急風
This makes sense
這個倒是一個道理
Because the convection is stronger in summer
因為夏天這個對流比較旺盛
Just like the convection just now
就像剛才那個對流一樣
so summer clouds
所以夏天的雲
A lot of them are like this kind of strange mountain.
很多很像這種很奇特的這種山峰一樣
autumn and winter clouds
秋天跟冬天的雲
Each has its own characteristics
各有它的特點
that this
那這個
Later this
後來這個
It may be the ring garden in the Ming Dynasty
可能是明朝那個戒指園
In the picture book, it is a great article about the cloud coming to heaven and earth
畫譜裡面就是說雲來天地之大文章
Qianyan of Mountains and Rivers is too busy in the future
山水之千岩往後卒意太忙碌
You have to draw some clouds when you draw too much this Qianyan
畫得太多這個千岩往後的時候你要畫一些雲
make him look slanted
讓他看起來斜一點
After that request, I am too willing to do so
那一求以後卒意太行
What are you going to do because there are so few things?
因為東西太少 你要怎麼辦呢
You also draw some shadows, he looks a little busy
你也畫一些影 他看起來就比較忙一點
So this has this wonderful effect
所以這個有這種奇妙的作用
I think what he said is quite reasonable.
我覺得他講得還滿有道理的
I found two examples, the first one is
我找了兩個例子出來 第一個是
These two are from the Yuan Dynasty. Wang Meng has one called
這兩個都是元朝的 王盟他有一個叫
Juquling Wutu, what about this pot?
聚屈靈烏土 這壺呢
Wang Meng is of course a Taoist of the Yuan Dynasty
王盟當然是元朝這個世道家
So of course his brush is very good
所以他這個畫筆當然是很好
But I think this earth dragon is too urgent
不過我看這個土龍是覺得這個實在太急了一點
It's like I can't breathe
好像透不過氣來這樣
The densely packed trees he drew are also stones
他畫的密密麻麻 樹也是石頭
If he can draw a little cloud in the middle
他如果中間可以畫一點雲的話
Looks like it's more likely not to be in such a hurry
看起來就比較可能不會那麼急
The other easel is better for him
那另外一個畫架他就比較好一點
He has a lot of mountains and fields, but there are some clouds in the middle of him.
他這個山野很多 可是他中間就弄了一些雲在那裡
Of course, the so-called cloud is actually the same as there is no painting
當然所謂雲在那裡其實就是等於沒有畫一樣
mostly blank
主要是空白
So it seems less urgent
所以看起來就比較沒那麼急
he doesn't feel like he can't breathe
他不會覺得透不過氣來的那樣子
So the cloud does have this magical effect
所以雲確實有這種妙用
Like this is Dong Qicha from the Ming Dynasty, Shu Hua's family
像這個是明朝的董奇叉 舒華家
He's not really that professional a painter
他其實不是真的那麼職業的畫家
Three strokes and two strokes of literati paintings by him
他畫的三筆兩筆文人畫
So he didn't have much time to draw in such detail
所以他沒有太多時間畫那麼詳細
So he used the awareness just now
所以他就用剛才這種意識
He said that you, Zhuo Yi, are too suspicious of a male Yun Mangzi
他就說你這個卓意太嫌出了男雲芒子
You just use that cloud to make it look like there's something in it
你就用那個雲把它看起來好像裡面有東西
So what he actually painted is the black place.
所以他這個東西其實畫的就是黑的地方
this place is left blank
這地方就是留著空白
But you seem to say it's a cloud
可是你看起來說這是雲
I would imagine that there might be trees behind that cloud
老子會想像說那個雲後面可能有樹
Actually he didn't say that
其實他也沒有這樣講
But that's what's in your head
可是你自然腦子就會這樣想說
There must be something behind that cloud
那個雲後面一定有東西
So this is the so-called Zhuo Yi too disliked
所以這就是所謂的卓意太嫌出
Male Yun Manzi makes him look a little more manly
男雲芒子讓他看起來芒一點
this is not bad
這個不錯
Therefore, Chinese painters
所以中國畫家對這個
There are many theories of phonetics
語音的理論倒是不少
But the modern voice
不過近代這個語音
That is to say, the voice painting in this Chinese painting is the best
就是說要講這個國畫裡面語音畫的最好
It may be the late Mr. Huang Junbi
可能是已故的這個黃君璧先生
His nickname is Master of Baiyun Hall
他字號叫做白雲堂主人
So I think he's already very, very confident with this voice painting
所以我想他已經對這個語音畫也非常非常有自信
That's true, his voice and painting are quite good.
那的確呢他這個語音畫的是相當好的
He painted voices better than those painters of previous generations
他畫得比前幾代的這些畫家畫的語音
He draws more realistically
他畫得更逼真一點
So this one is one of his rhythms
所以這張是他的節奏之一
He often mentions a
他常常在他的畫上面提一個
Looking at the green mountains and deep white clouds are all the feelings of hometown
一望青山深白麗白雲都是故鄉情
also very realistic
也很有實情畫意
But I have one dissatisfaction with our Chinese painter
不過我對我們這個國畫家有一個不滿的地方
Dissatisfaction is that
不滿的地方就是說
Half the day they drew his clouds looked the same
他們畫的半天他的雲看起來都一樣
He didn't try to draw other clouds
他都沒有嘗試去畫別的雲
He also didn't try to draw cloud shadows
他也沒有嘗試去畫雲的影子
Its camp is basically next to the mountain
它營基本上就是旁著那個山
Then there are some clouds
然後就是有一些浮雲
So after talking for half a day
所以講了半天的時候
The main purpose of its cloud painting is to set off the mountains
主要它的畫雲的目的是要襯托這些山
That's all
這樣而已
So although it has a lot of theory about painting clouds
所以它雖然很多畫雲的理論
it doesn't really execute
它沒有真的去執行
How should the cloud be drawn, how to draw, how to draw
那個雲應該怎麼畫 怎麼畫 怎麼畫
So at least I read a lot about the Forbidden City.
所以至少故宮的話我也看了不少
It seems that I haven't really found a serious one.
好像沒有真的找到一個很認真的
Example of drawing that different cloud
把那個不同的雲畫出來的例子
But speaking of Western paintings
不過話說西洋畫
It's almost like that in ancient times
好像古代也差不多那個樣子
it doesn't matter
它也不管
When we draw clouds, we draw a cloud
大家畫雲就是畫一朵雲
And the cloud in the ancient western paintings is not the main character
而且古代的西洋畫那個雲更是不是主角
Ancient paintings are all figures
古代的畫都是人物
so be the protagonist
所以做這種主角
Then draw a cloud in that least heavy corner
然後在那個最不重的角落畫一個雲
It seems like a place full of clouds
好像浩雲浩雲的地方
This probably lasted until the Impressionist came out.
這個大概一直到這個印象派出來以後
I really started to pay attention to that cloud
才真的開始注重那個雲的
Draw that cloud very realistically
把那個雲畫得很逼真
And not only the clouds are very realistic
而且不但雲很逼真
That kind of scene turns into clouds and shines on each other
那種景物變成雲互相光
Various coordination between online
在線之間的各種配合
very well drawn
畫得非常好
This is the master of impressionism
這個是印象派的大師
his master
他的主師
This one is called Caude Monet
這個叫做Caude Monet
painted
所畫的
He speaks from the point of view of this cloudy school
他以這種雲霧的學校的觀點來講
he drew it exactly right
他畫得完全正確
Exactly like Convection Shadow
完全就像對流影的樣子
Ba Xiao
霸小
And where should his shadow be?
還有他這個影子應該在哪裡
Then the bottom should look like
然後底部應該是什麼樣子
I have nothing to say
我沒有好講
that's him
就是他這個
Indeed, the painting is very, very
的確畫的是非常非常的
lifelike
逼真
just that part
剛才那一段
I think
我覺得
although i can't draw
雖然我不會畫
but i think
但是我覺得
if you study hard
如果好好學的話
very well said
說得很可以畫
But after I saw this
可是我看到這一張以後
I said that there is nothing I can do about it
我說那這個我沒有辦法
I don't think I can draw this
這種我覺得畫不出來
my first time in
我第一次在
I'm in Paris, France
我在法國巴黎那個
that
那個
I was actually at a place called Caude Pong
我最早其實在一個叫Caude Pong
that that that that
那個那個那個
when i saw this picture
我看到這一張畫的時候
just thought about it
就想了一想
Somebody come in and really can draw
有人進來真的可以畫出
get this cloud out
把這種雲出來
One of the reasons is that
其中之一個原因就是說
The first one I am very sensitive to this cloud
第一個我對這種雲非常敏感
Every time the sky derails this cloud
我每次天空出軌這種雲
My whole body is uncomfortable
我的滿身都很不舒服
I just said I've been thinking about it for a long time and I can't figure it out
我剛說都一直想了很久都想不通
Later I figured out why
後來我都想通為什麼會這樣
so i'll explain later
所以我等一下再解釋
But I've ever felt that way
不過我自從有那種感覺
That is, if anyone can take the cloud
就是如果誰可以把雲
That kind of cloud can be drawn with that brush
那種雲用那個畫筆可以畫得出來
I admire it very much
那我是非常佩服它
I ended up visiting this museum.
結果竟然去參觀這個博物館
There is such a painting in this demon
竟然這個魔內它就有這一幅畫這種
This means it's not sunny
這種就是說它不是晴天
but it's not raining
可是它也不是下雨
It's half sunny and half rainy
就是那種半晴天半下雨
at a glance
一看就
When I saw it, I felt that the cloud was really uncomfortable.
我一看就覺得雲真的不舒服
That's an amazing art too
那也是一種不得了的藝術就是
So this is very, very powerful
所以這個非常非常厲害
I don't see anyone else drawing
我就沒有看到別人可以畫出
draw it like this
像這樣子的畫出來
that mentioned why
那提到為什麼那樣子
Just look at this picture first
就先看這一張圖再說
This one is the so-called high-speed luck
這一張是所謂的高機運
You may often see this
大家可能常常會看到這種運
What impression do you usually have when you see this kind of luck?
大家看到這種運通常會有什麼印象
what kind of weather do you usually live in
你通常會在什麼樣的天氣之下
See what Gao Jiyun looks like
看到高機運像是什麼樣
like a fish spirit
像魚靈一樣
Does anyone care to guess
有沒有人願意猜一下
Or tell me about your usual impression
或者把你的平常的印象講一下
actually not
其實不是
This kind of luck is good when the weather is good
這種運多吧是天氣上好的時候
Yulingtian
魚靈天
This kind of high-speed luck is usually when the sky is better
這種高機運常常都是天比較好的時候
and the background can often be seen through
而且背景往往都可以透過
see above that blue sky
看到那個藍天的上面
This is actually mentioned in many elementary and middle school textbooks
這個很多小學的中學課本其實都有提到
But when he mentioned it he often said
但是他提到的時候常常說
If you see this cloud like fish spirit
你如果看到這種像魚靈一樣的雲
yes means sunny
是代表是晴天
I think this sentence is a bit redundant
我覺得這句話其實有點多餘
This sentence is of course true
這句話當然是對的
So this is of little significance, it should be like this, that is to say, if you see this kind of cloud, and then it becomes a piece, and becomes a whole cloud, it means that the weather is going to be bad
所以這個意義不大,應該是這樣,就是說如果是體現看到這種雲,然後它變成一片,變成一種整成的雲,那就代表天氣要變壞了
Why? Because when you have this kind of cloud, it usually represents small-scale convection, one by one small convection packets, and it is not very deep, it is a small and shallow convection, so it is not itself not thick
為什麼呢?因為你有這種雲的時候,通常代表小尺度的這種對流,一個一個一個小對流包,而且它不是很深,它是一個小的很淺的一種對流,所以它已經本身並不厚
But if they are connected together, it means that there is a large-scale movement approaching, so the whole air will rise upwards
可是它如果連成一片,那就代表有一個大規模的運動要接近了,所以整個空氣整成都往上升
When you see this convection, some of the air rises and some of it goes down, but when you see the whole becomes one piece, then the weather starts to get bad
你當你看到這個對流的時候,空氣有的往上升,有的往下升,可是當你看到整個變成一片的時候,那個時候天氣就開始變不好
If it's the other way around, you first see a large layer of cloud formation, and then come on, it suddenly becomes this
如果是反過來,你先看到一大層的成雲,然後再來,它突然變成這個
the weather will get better
那天氣一定變好
This situation means that when I was a freshman or sophomore
這個情況就是說我念大一還是大二的時候
I just learned a little bit about this
剛好懂了一點這個東西
very happy
很高興
I just got married
剛好我到一個結婚
it rained heavily that morning
那天早上下大雨
Of course everyone is very troubled
大家當然很煩惱
It's finally raining
總算下雨這個
It's inconvenient to get married when it rains
結婚是下雨很不方便
Trouble with guests
客人來也麻煩
Sometimes I told him that I hadn't studied the heptathlon
有時候我跟他說自身不是念過七項學
Soon about ten o'clock
不久以後差不多到十點的時候
I saw that the blue sky began to have a few pieces of this small
就看到那個藍天一腳開始有幾塊這種小小的
This kind of high-speed machine looks like it came out
這種高機運的樣子出來
I'm bold enough to tell my father
我很大膽跟我父親講說
Don't worry, the weather will improve
放心等一下天氣會變好
Sure enough, more than an hour
果然一個多鐘頭
Slowly and slowly the whole cost becomes the whole rain
慢慢慢慢整成本來是整成的雨
slowly become like this
慢慢就變成這種
rain like rain
像雨嶺一樣的雨
In the afternoon, it was simply the situation.
到下午根本就是情況發明
So I'm very impressed with doing
所以我從事就印象非常深刻
It's a good day to see high altitude clouds
看到高機雲這個天氣很好
Everyone knows about this painting
那這個繪畫這個大家知道
The problem is that you want to change the shape of the cloud from this
問題是你要從這個雲的形狀的改變
go see what the weather will be like
去看看天氣會變成什麼樣子
which is more important
哪一點比較重要
so you want to understand this
那你為了要了解這個
Of course you need to understand
當然你要了解說
Where did this cloud come from?
到底這個雲是怎麼來的
so after knowing this
所以知道這些以後
It's more interesting to look at the cloud
看雲就會比較有趣一點
Some western flower family even even clouds
西洋花家有的甚至連雲的
Those were a little more static
剛才那些都比較靜態一點
The painting is a little dynamic
這幅畫有點動態
because it draws clouds
因為它出的畫了雲
This is clearly a dense cloud
這個很顯然是一種密集雲
and it's beyond the clouds
而且它雲之外
look at the windy direction
你看看它這個有風的風向
sometimes see that cloud
有時候看到那個雲
especially in autumn
尤其是秋天的時候
The higher wind is stronger
那個高的風比較強一點
It can blow clouds from side to side
它可以把雲從一邊往另外一邊吹
you can see this cloud
你可以看到這個雲的
so-called wind shear
所謂的風切的現象
so it's obvious
所以這個很顯然
The wind on this upper level blows from the right to the left
這個高層的風是從右邊吹向左邊
This is an American painter's Junker
這是一個美國畫家的Junker
He just made it so that he wasn't really one of us.
他畫的剛好就是他其實不是我們那一員
But the scenery he painted
可是他畫的景色
It’s just the scenery near the Metis where I live
就是剛好我住的那個Metis附近的景色
exactly like this
的確就完全像這種樣子
some countryside then some trees
一些農村然後一些樹
And did you see that autumn really is
然後你有沒有看到秋天真的是
This very high cloud then goes in a certain direction
這種很高的雲然後往某一個方向
I just asked my students
我才問我學生說
After you see this painting, is there any way to warm it up on the ground?
你看到這個畫以後有沒有辦法把他的地面溫度
As the altitude changes then the wind on the ground follows the wind direction at altitude
隨著高空的改變然後地面的風跟隨著高空的風向
We call the explorer refusal, is there a way to write it out?
我們叫探工拒權有沒有辦法把它寫出來
It should be possible
照講應該是可以的
If you are familiar with the terroir of a place
你如果對一個地方的風土夠熟悉的話
In addition to these individual clouds just now
除了剛才這些個別的雲之外
I have all kinds of scenery
我還有各式各樣的景色
Like our sea of ​​clouds, a friend of mine named Zhuang Kaihua took this picture
像我們雲海這個我一個朋友叫莊凱華他拍的
This one is in Miaoli
這個反而是在苗栗
Miaoli seems to be called crow leaf or something
苗栗好像一個叫什麼烏鴉葉還是什麼
where we are over there
我們在那邊的地方
we go camping over there
我們在那邊去露營
We often see this in Taiwan
我們台灣常常可以看到這種
The whole cloud submerges the mountain like the sea
整個雲像海一樣把山淹沒
So it's a cloud phenomenon
所以這是一種雲的現象
often in the valley
常常在山谷裡面
early in the morning
一大早
maybe the weather is nice
可能天氣很好
But slowly the wind blows
可是慢慢的風一來
you can see the whole valley
你可以看到這個整個山谷
empty full of clouds
空滿了雲
a piece exactly like the sea
一片完全像海一樣
So this sea of ​​clouds is really like a sea of ​​clouds
所以這個雲海真的像雲海
Yunshan is really a mountain
雲山那也真的是山
This is the plane I took
這個是我拍的這個飛機
Already flew at a peak of about 12,000 meters
已經飛在大概一萬兩千公尺的高峰
But because of the clouds above
可是因為雲的上面
taller than this plane
比這個飛機還高
Twelve thousand meters
這一萬兩千公尺
world's highest peak
世界最高峰
Come to Mount Everest this time
這個時候來Mount Everest
Or I will code the wind in mainland China
或者中國大陸我來碼風
Only more than 8000 less than 9000 meters
才8000多不到9000公尺
So if you move Inoki male king to
所以你如果把豬木男王搬到
same place
同樣這個地方
still below
還在下面
Clouds in our Taiwan summer
我們台灣夏天的雲
It's just ten kilometers
隨便就是十幾公里
The kind of summer that makes cloud-based tops
那種夏天的讓基於雲的頂
About 12 to 13 kilometers
大約都在12 13公里
At least
至少
When it is more vigorous, sometimes 15
比較旺盛的時候有時候15
15 6 km
15 6公里
are very high clouds
是非常高的雲
Your so-called highest peak in the world is actually still
你這個所謂的世界最高峰其實都還
still much lower than that
還在還比那個低的多了
Simply
根本就是
89 kilometers like this
89公里這樣子而已
This is also based on
這個也是基於
This is all you can see if you look at him from a plane based on
這個都是你如果從飛機上看他你可以看到基於
Basically, it grows long and long from a very low place a few hundred meters
基本上就是從很低的地方幾百公尺就一直長長長
grow to
長到
ten kilometers high
十幾公里高
So if you haven't been to this Everest
所以你如果沒有去過這個聖母峰
if moved in front of your eyes
如果搬到你眼前
how high will it be
大概會有多高
It's not really that high
其實也沒有真的那麼高
So this can give you a better reference point is
所以這個可以給你一個比較好的參考點就是
Of course not all clouds are happy
當然不是所有的雲都很愉快
Some clouds look a little scary
有的雲看起來也有點恐怖的
This is called a milky advanced cloud
這個叫乳狀高級雲
This is usually in this kind of cloud with this storm
這個通常是在這種跟這個風暴的雲
very relevant cloud
非常有關係的雲
You can see it this below
你可以看到它這個下面
Round and round, a bit like that cow
一圈一圈的有點像那個乳牛一樣
Saggy bunch of this cow's milk like
下垂的一大堆這種奶牛的奶一樣
So we call it milky high cloud
所以我們叫做乳狀高級雲
I remember Li He in the Tang Dynasty
我記得以前這個唐朝這個李鶴
Also wrote a poem called Black Cloud
也寫了一首詩叫做黑雲
Duck City Chen Yuchui
鴨城陳玉垂
The false light is like golden clouds blooming on the sun
假光像日金雲開
he wrote this scene
他寫的這個景象
I think it's exactly like the scene I took that time
我覺得滿像就是我那次拍到的景象一樣
This is the so-called milky advanced cloud
這個就是所謂的乳狀高級雲
how did this come about
這個到底怎麼產生的
now everyone is arguing
現在大家還在爭論
have different theories
有不同的理論
But why would he cause
可是他為什麼會造成
It just so happens that this kind of spherical shape is very strange.
剛好這種圓球狀的很奇怪
Gao Jin's advocacy just now also looks strange.
剛才那種主狀高進也看起來很奇怪
But it's not scary
不過還不至於很恐怖
This movie is more scary
這個影比較恐怖一點
This shadow is what we call the strong shadow
這個影是我們叫強壯影
Walk on
Walk on
basically you can see this ground
基本上你可以看到這個地面
This shadow is like a big one of this kind
這個影就像一個很大的這種
Vacuum cleaner blows down from the sky again
真空吸塵器從天空再吹下來
If you just stood below
你如果剛才站在下面
The hot water is sucked up
受熱水被吸上去了
It's like an alien machine
是很像外星人的這種機器一樣
Of course you see this cloud
當然你看到這種雲
i think you better run faster
我想你最好跑快一點
Because this kind of shadow is the precursor of a tornado
因為這種影是龍捲風要出現的這種前兆
This cloud usually appears
通常出現這種雲
Signs of a tornado
龍捲風出現的前兆
This wall-like circle of clouds
這種像牆壁一樣的一大圈的雲
Then it's slowly turning
然後它的慢慢的轉動
That tornado doesn't seem to appear slowly
那個龍捲好像不是慢慢出現
some slowly
有的是慢慢的
but there are
可是有的是
when you look happy like this
你這樣看得高興的時候
it came suddenly
它突然來了
Maybe it's right in front of your eyes
說不定就是剛好在你眼前
Suddenly a tornado appeared
就突然冒出一個龍捲好處
it will be like this
就會這樣
So when you see this cloud phenomenon
所以當你看到有這種雲的現象的時候
This is to find a place to hide
這個是趕快找個地方躲
or lower your voice
或者呼低一點
Maybe it's safer
可能比較保險一點
Those just now are not very scientific
剛才那些都是不太科學
those are a chat
那些都是一種聊天
let's take a look now
我們現在稍微看一看
Where did the cloud come from?
雲到底是怎麼來的
The elements of the cloud are not there in the end
雲的要素最終沒有在那
That's it
就是這樣
First
第一個
Clouds must have water vapor
雲一定要有水蒸氣
We say that clouds are mainly made of water
我們講雲主要是水造成的雲
If you have another smoke cause
你如果再有一個煙造成
that doesn't count
那個不算
Speaking of this water vapor
在講到這個水蒸氣
you mention again
你再提到說
Here we sometimes talk about the so-called man-made cloud
這邊有時候再講所謂的人造雲
Say wow, no, we are in a drought, we need to hurry up and make rain
說哇不行啦,我們在旱災了,要趕快人造雨啦
But drought, what does drought mean?
可是旱災啊,旱災什麼意思?
You are almost out of water
你這幾乎是沒有水啦
True droughts are very, very rare in representations of water in the air
真正的旱災在代表空氣中的水成型都非常非常稀少
absolutely not
根本沒有
How do you make rain when you have no water at all?
你根本沒有水你怎麼造雨呢?
no way
沒有辦法
So I made a skylight question, do you have any comments?
所以我做了一個天窗題,大家有沒有什麼意見?
What is the south of the bridge, what is nothing, what is known
橋什麼南圍,無什麼,知什麼東西
Anyone want to try it?
有沒有人要嘗試一下?
In fact, this is not an answer, the answer is up to you
其實這個不是一個答案啦,這個答案隨便你
say what you want
隨便你怎麼講的啦
I made this
我這個是我造的啦
if you have no water at all
你如果根本沒有水
Even if you are a god, you cannot create clouds
你就是神仙你也造不出雲出來
There is no water to make it, you are making too much of this
根本沒有水可以造啊,你就在弄多的這種
It's useless to throw away stippling silver or something like that
點畫銀什麼之類的,你再去丟根本沒有用
So if you want clouds, first of all, of course you must form water
所以你要有雲,第一當然你一定要水成型
Sometimes there is water vapor, but sometimes there is no cloud, why?
水蒸氣有時候常常有,可是有時候就是沒有雲,為什麼?
Because the water vapor has to be saturated to be able to
因為那個水蒸氣要達到飽和才可以
So the second one is that you have to reach saturation
所以第二個就是說,你這個要達到飽和
What does it mean to be saturated?
那所謂飽和是什麼意思呢?
The first one is that your water vapor content must be sufficient
第一個就是說,你的水蒸氣的含量一定要足夠的多
Second, sometimes there is a lot of water vapor, you will feel very stuffy
第二個,有時候水蒸氣含量也很多,你會覺得很悶
But the sky is still very bright with few and no clouds
可是天空還是很亮,幾乎沒有,也沒有雲
But you feel dazed and sad, why?
但是你覺得全身發懵,覺得很難過,為什麼?
Because it has not reached saturation, then under what circumstances will it reach saturation
因為它沒有達到飽和,那在什麼情況之下它要達到飽和
That kind of saturation has a lot to do with temperature and air temperature.
那種飽和跟溫度跟氣溫非常有關係
Therefore, the water vapor content and the temperature must be coordinated with each other.
所以水蒸氣含量跟氣溫兩個要互相配合
to saturate the cloud
才可以使雲達到飽和
These two things are actually related to the movement of air.
那這兩個東西其實跟空氣的運動都很有關係
What is air movement called?
空氣運動叫什麼?
air movement that is called wind
空氣運動那個叫做風
Of course it's wind and water
那當然就是風之水
just one of them
其中的一種而已
Usually we call horizontal movement
通常我們把水平運動叫做
is called the wind
才叫做風
The wind from east to west, from north to south
東西南北風這種風
This is to say that the air is a horizontal movement
這個是講空氣是水平運動
But the air has to move up and down
可是空氣也要上下流動
At that time it was not called the wind
那時候又不把它叫風
updraft or downdraft
上升氣流或者成降氣流
then this is
那這是
turn this
轉這個
talk about this up and down
講這個上上下下的
general cloud formation
一般雲的形成跟
updraft relationship
上升氣流的關係
relatively close
比較密切
comparison means
比較意思就是說
some in
有的在
There are of course other possibilities under individual circumstances.
個別狀況之下當然還有別的可能性
but the updraft
但是上升氣流
The relationship is particularly great
的關係特別大
that might
那可能
a little unforgettable
有一點難忘
That is to say, the horizontal movement of the air is
就是說空氣的水平運動跟
What is the difference in vertical movement?
垂直運動到底有什麼不一樣
This difference is very large
這個差異非常大
just with you
就跟你
usually walk on flat road
平常在平路走路
follow you up the mountain
跟你上山
Also walk a mile to see
同樣走一公里看看
Generally similar
一般也類似
you see this is different
你看這個就不一樣
But for the air
可是對空氣來講
what is its biggest difference
它的最大的不同在什麼地方
its biggest difference
它最大的不同
vertical movement of air
空氣的垂直運動
The change in air pressure it experiences is very large
它所經歷的氣壓的改變非常大
if you level
你如果水平的話
it doesn't change air pressure
它氣壓沒有什麼改變
In general, a large area
一般一個廣大地區來講
its air pressure is about the same
它的氣壓差不多都一樣
So your air if in the same area
所以你空氣如果在同一個地區
move around
動來動去
If it is a horizontal movement
如果是水平運動的話
its air pressure hasn't changed
它的氣壓沒有什麼改變
But if it is vertical
可是它如果垂直的話
it's totally different
它完全不一樣
Ordinary air, if it runs upwards,
一般空氣它如果往上跑的話
what consequences will it have
它會有什麼後果
when an air goes up
當一個空氣往上跑的時候
The pressure outside is suddenly less
外面的壓力突然變少
we all know
我們大家知道說
The higher the altitude, the thinner the air
越往高空氣越來越稀薄
right
對不對
some people have mountain sickness
有的人有高山病
That altitude sickness is another
那高山病是另外一隻
But Takayama has a very serious
可是高山有一個很嚴重的
In the mountains, the air is thinner
高山的話空氣比較稀薄
Some people are not used to it
有的人就很不習慣
Some people even outside
有的人就算是在外面
will be confused
就會混倒
that almost everyone
那幾乎所有的人
except for local residents
除了當地居民
If you go to the mountain with a height of about 5,000 meters
你如果到那個高到大概五千公尺的山
Almost all of them will come across more or less
差不多都會多多少少的大概遇到
So, for example, when it comes to the shoreland 13 in South America
所以譬如說到南美洲的那個岸地十三
That place is five or six thousand meters
那個地方都是五六千公尺
People who are not used to it can't stand that height
不是習慣的人都受不了那種高度
why
為什麼呢
Because it is very air-absorbing
因為它空氣非常吸附
The air is very attracted to you
空氣非常吸附你這個
Inhaled air, the oxygen content is not enough
吸進來空氣這個含氧量不夠
Let you this can't produce enough heat
讓你這個產生不不了足夠的讓熱量
So this air is getting more and more absorbed
所以這個空氣越來越吸附
This is a very important phenomenon
這是一個很重要的現象
when you have a cloud of air
當你有一團空氣
when going up
往上升的時候
outside air adsorption
外面的空氣吸附
on behalf of
就代表
Because the air is supposed to have pressure, right?
因為空氣本來是會有壓力對不對
Then you are under so much pressure
那你這個壓力本來這麼大
When it rises suddenly, the pressure outside it decreases
突然往上升的時候它外面壓力減小
Then it will start to expand outward
接下來它會開始往外膨脹
What will be the consequences of this expansion in the past?
這個以往外膨脹會有什麼後果
If a mass of air expands outward
一團空氣如果往外膨脹
without other sources of heat
而沒有其他熱的來源的話
It's one of the greatest possibilities it will get cold
它的一個最大可能性它就會變冷
So when an air it expands
所以當一個空氣它一膨脹
As it rises and expands it cools
一往上升一膨脹它就變冷
Once it got cold, there was some water vapor in it
一變冷以後它本來裡面有一些水蒸氣
The water vapor is originally called unsaturated
那個水蒸氣本來所謂的未飽和
Because under the condition of relatively high temperature
因為在那種比較溫度比較高的情況之下
it does not reach saturation
它沒有達到飽和
But when you get cold
可是當你一變冷的時候
It may slowly this saturation
它可能就慢慢這個飽和度
Higher and higher
越來越高
it may not necessarily reach saturation
它可能不見得達到飽和
but maybe 90 percent saturated
但是可能百分之九十飽和
Then lift it up
那再往上抬
In the end it really saturates
到最後它說真的就達到飽和
As long as the air goes up
只要空氣越往上升
it's getting colder
它越來越冷
cloud of dry air
一團乾空氣
Or even a cloud of air with water vapor in it
或者甚至一團空氣裡面帶有水蒸氣
it goes up
它往上升
As long as there is no condensation
只要還沒有產生凝結現象的時候
it lifts a kilometer
它抬升一公里
it's about ten degrees lower
它大概會減低十度
so cold
所以滿冷的喔
A cloud of air is on the ground if twenty degrees
一團空氣在地面如果二十度
You lifted it two thousand meters
你給它抬了兩千公尺
it will be zero degrees freezing point
它會變成零度 冰點
So this is a big change
所以這個是很厲害的變化
A cloud of air rises two meters from the ground, after two thousand meters
一團空氣從地面升了兩公尺 兩千公尺以後
Alishan Alishan is not even 2,000 meters away
阿里山 阿里山也不夠兩千公尺而已
If a cloud of air rises from the ground to the height of Alishan
一團空氣如果從地面升到阿里山的高度
The air inside can become freezing point.
裡面的空氣能得很啊 變成冰點
then you may find it strange
那你可能會覺得奇怪
But Alishan is not always freezing point
可是阿里山也不是什麼時候都是冰點
Of course the so-called what I just said is
那當然所謂的 我剛才講這個就是
That is only if the air has movement
那是要空氣有運動才算
But usually the air in Alishan is not from sports.
可是平常阿里山那空氣那可不是運動來的
That's another mechanic, that's another story
那是另外一個機制來的 那是另外一個故事
I won't mention it for now
我暫時不提那裡
What I want to mention here is that
我這邊要提的就是說
If you have a cloud of air rising up the table
假如你有一團空氣往上台升
For two kilometers, it was originally twenty degrees and it became zero degrees.
兩公里的話 本來二十度它變成零度
Because every kilometer it cools down ten degrees
因為每公里它會降溫十度
The same cloud of air if from a high altitude
同樣的一團空氣如果從高空
sinking for some reason
由於某種原因往下沉
It's going to be a day and it's going to be a very very day
它會變得一日 最後會變成非常非常日
This is actually thermodynamics
這個其實是熱力學
Thermodynamics means
熱力學就是說
Adiabatic expansion cools
絕熱的膨脹會變冷
Adiabatic compression heats an air
絕熱的壓縮會使一個空氣變熱
Then this thing with a
那這個東西跟一個
it has something to do with your flight
你坐飛機有一點關係
Usually we fly
坐飛機通常我們這個
start from the ground
從地面開始
The ground air probably has us or something
地面空氣大概有我們什麼的
around 1000 mbar
1000毫巴左右
You fly so high
你一飛飛到那麼高空
About 200 millibars left
大概剩下200毫巴
so the air has
所以空氣已經
That pressure has been reduced by 1.5
那個壓力已經少了1.5
if that air
如果那個空氣
If the cabin doesn't pressurize the air
那個機艙沒有把空氣加壓的話
you will feel very sad
你會覺得非常難過
Because the air is too thin
因為那個空氣太稀薄
So the captain must use
所以那個機長一定要用
big compressor
很大的這種壓縮機
press that air to
把那個空氣壓到
very stressful
壓力非常大
almost as big as the ground
大到幾乎跟地面一樣
sometimes say 90%
有時候譬如說90%
and put that air in
然後把那個空氣進來
into this cabin to let you
到這個機艙裡面讓你
let you breathe
讓你呼吸
you will feel very natural
你會覺得很自然
Then we just talked about the air
那我們剛才講說空氣
So if you compress that
所以如果把那個壓縮的話
it gets hot
它會變熱
Will high altitude be able to?
高空會不會 也會
When the captain sucks in the air
當這個機長把這個空氣抽進來以後
Then heat it up and put it in
然後把它加熱 加熱放進來以後
If it doesn't put this air
它如果沒有再把這個空氣
after that cold
經過一個那個冷
if the air conditioner cools it down
空氣調節把它冷掉的話
The temperature is about 60 degrees
那個溫度大概60度左右
everyone will be hot
大家會熱死
Rick it's all over
李克全部都完蛋了
So when it shakes this air into the cabin
所以它把這個空氣晃到機艙裡面的時候
It must be air-conditioned first
它一定要先用空調
pump this excess heat off
把這個多餘的熱量把它抽掉
So that consumes a very, very large amount of energy
所以那個是耗費非常非常大的這種能量
It is to put this pressurized hot air
就是要把這個加壓以後的熱空氣
let it cool down and put it in this cabin
再把它冷卻然後再放到這個機艙裡面
So this is a very, very fuel-intensive thing
所以這個是非常非常耗油的東西
Even if you still have to spend some oil to deal with these problems
就是你還是要花一些油去處理這些問題
Even if the temperature outside the cabin at that time
即使那個時候機艙外面的溫度
maybe minus sixty or seventy degrees
可能是零下六七十度
It still needs to get this air to cool it down
它還是需要把這個空氣把它冷卻
Relying on the outside air temperature is not enough
靠外面的空氣溫度是不行的
Use this air conditioner to send the cooling back in again
用這種冷氣機再把冷卻再送進來
So this is called the expansion of the air
所以這就是所謂的空氣的膨脹
A very important reason for the cooling of the camp
降溫產生營的一個很重要的原因
So basically come this is called
所以基本上來這就是所謂的
The basic mechanism is
基本上的機制就是
The mechanism of forming a camp is mainly here
成營的機制主要是這邊
A cloud of air with water vapor
一團空氣帶有水蒸氣
it cools as it goes up
它往上升的時候它會冷卻
because of swelling
因為膨脹
after cooling
冷卻以後呢
It will reach saturation
能到模樣程度它會達到飽和
Once saturated
一旦到飽和
In theory its condensation should produce
理論上它的凝結就應該產生
At that time you will see the clouds come out
那個時候你就要看到雲出來
So the picture below represents a cloud
所以下面這一張就是代表一個雲的
A basic mechanism of cloud formation
成雲的一個基本的機制
A mass of air has no water droplets in it
一團空氣本來裡面沒有水滴
but there is water vapor
但是有水蒸氣
Go up and slowly get bigger and bigger
往上升慢慢越來越大
to a certain extent
到了某一個程度
After they are saturated with water vapor,
它們裡面水蒸氣達到飽和以後
Ectopic Concrete
達到氣象上叫做舉生凝結層
By this time you should see that cloud start to come out
這個時候你應該看到那個雲開始出來了
This is the so-called bottom of the cloud, the cloud base is starting to come out
這是所謂的雲的底部 雲底開始出來了
And the cloud if it still has enough water in it
然後雲 如果它裡面還有足夠的水的話
it will keep going up and you can see the clouds
它會一直繼續往上升 然後你可以看到雲
keep showing up and that weird place
繼續一直出現 而且那個很奇怪的地方
That is to say, once it has an air lift up
就是說它一旦有一個空氣往上抬升的話
The other air pocket below is probably coming up from the same place
下面另外一個空氣包可能就是從同一個地方來上來
Because once you have one air and one goes up
因為你一旦有一個空氣一個往上升的話
You can easily drive other places to bring in the air
你很容易帶動其他的地方把那個空氣湊進來
And from there the new air rises up
然後從那個地方 新的空氣再往上升
The new air has other new sources of water vapor in it
新的空氣裡面又帶有其他的新的水蒸氣來源
So you see a cloud rising far away
所以你看到一朵雲 遠遠不斷地一直漲
it's cause like this up out
它的原因就像是這樣子 漲出來
So let's talk nonsense, let's watch this kind of cloud-making movie
所以空口說白話 我們來看看這種成雲的電影
This is the so-called move of Yundi just now
這就是剛才雲底就是所謂的舉動
We can see the phenomenon we just mentioned
可以看到我們剛才提到的這種現象
you see it keeps going up
你看到一直往上漲
I can't see anything below why
下面什麼都看不到 為什麼
because of water vapor
因為水蒸氣嘛
Water vapor is so transparent you can't see it at all
水蒸氣透明的你根本看不到
In fact the air is always going up
事實上空氣一直在往上升
But because it is transparent
可是因為它透明
contains water vapor
包含水蒸氣
so you can't see
所以你看不到
you can't see it going up
你看不到它往上漲
In fact, there are constantly new air bags
其實不斷的有新的空氣包
come in here
從這裡進來
then always
然後一直
for this cloud
等於是為這朵雲
A lot of new water vapor comes out
很多新的水蒸氣出來
If there is enough water vapor in a place,
一個地方如果水蒸氣夠多的話
Clouds can always go up
雲可以一直往上增漲
even grown to thunder and lightning
甚至增長到可以打雷閃電
Why does the air go up
空氣為什麼要往上升
wait a second
等一下還有打
The little teacher didn't want to see through everyone's past
小老師不是想要透看大家這個以前
wait a minute let me see
等一下啦我看一下
You asked exactly the topic I chose
你問的正好就是我選的題目
Why does the air rise so high
空氣為什麼要很上升
there are several theories
有好幾個理論
several reasons
好幾個理由
The first is convection
第一個是對流
under the same air pressure
在同樣的氣壓之下
If the air in this place is warmer
如果這個地方空氣比較暖的話
Its density will become a little lighter
它的密度會變得比較輕一點
So it creates a force
所以它就產生一種伏力
For a light air is like
因為一個輕的空氣就好像
an air bubble in water
一個空氣泡在水裡面
relatively small density
密度比較小
So it will rise with a force
所以它會有一個伏力就往上升
So this is one of the first
所以這是一個其中第一個
Usually this convection is called free convection
通常這種對流叫做自由對流
because it's all temperature dependent
因為它完全是溫度的關係
The first is a forced convection
第一個是一種強迫對流
forced convection
強迫性對流
inside the weather inside the air
在天氣裡面空氣裡面
This is usually
這種通常都是
For example, there is a very cold air
譬如說有一種很冷的空氣
Very cold air generally
很冷的空氣一般來講
it's a bit heavier
它的重量比較重一點
when it starts moving
當它開始動的時候
There are many things moving, and the rotation of the earth will also drive it
動的也很多,地球在轉也會帶動它
It doesn't rotate at the same time as the earth
它又不是跟地球同樣一個時候轉
It sometimes spins at a different speed than the Earth
它有時候轉的速度跟地球不一樣
So anyway, it still has relative motion with the ground
所以反正它跟地面還有相對運動
Then once such cold air moves
那一旦這麼冷的空氣動的時候
it will make the front lighter
它會使得前面的比較輕
or warmer air would be lifted by it
或者比較暖的空氣會被它抬起來
The air, the air in front is not necessarily warmer
那那個空氣,前面空氣它也不見得比較暖
But it is also forced by it
可是它也被它強迫
Because of its sense of movement is forced by it
因為它的運動的感覺被它強迫
it winds it up like an opener
它像一個開爐機一樣把它纏起來一樣
So it's called compulsive, compulsive uplifting
所以它叫做強迫性,強迫性的抬升
Then once the air may be reluctant
那一旦空氣可能不情不願的
It is unwilling to rise, but because of its movement
它不願意上升,可是被它這個運動的關係
so be lifted by it
所以被它抬起來
What should I do after I lift it up? It's the same
那抬起來以後怎麼辦?也一樣啊
It also expands and cools when lifted
抬起來以後它也會膨脹,也會冷卻
Then come the clouds
然後就來產生雲出來
That's because this kind of movement usually has a larger scale
那因為這種運動它通常是尺度比較大一點
So it's whole, it's a movement
所以它整個,它這個一動的話
The whole floor has gone up
整層都已經往上升
So the clouds you see act like clouds
所以你看到的雲,動作都是像成雲
Because the large area is full of clouds
因為大片全部是成雲蓋的滿滿的
That hair is the weather will get worse
那個頭髮都是天氣會變得比較不好
because it is a large-scale movement
因為它是一種大尺度的運動
that's why i just said
這就是為什麼我剛才講說
If it was a high-flying
如果本來是高機運
And then it becomes the whole layer all connected
然後它變成整層的全部都連起來
the weather may turn bad
那天氣可能會變不好
It is because of this large-scale movement
就是因為這種大尺度的運動
The other is volatility
另外一個是波動
Fluctuations This is usually caused by relatively small movements
波動這個通常是造成比較小規模的運動
The so-called fluctuation is like water waves
那所謂波動就是像水波一樣
Water wave, you throw away the silk and go into the water
水波你丟開絲綢到水面裡面
Look at it spreading out in waves
你看看它一個波往外傳
A wave spreads out as if moving
一個波往外傳好像在動
But the water itself is not flowing
可是那個水本身其實沒有在流
The water itself is actually just moving up and down
水本身其實只是在上下動而已
But that wave looks like it's been running out
可是那個波看起來好像一直在往外跑
it just runs outside
它只是往外跑而已
The water itself must be flowing
那個水本身一定流動的沒有
If you throw a piece of wood on the water
你如果丟一塊木頭在水上面
The log didn't run away either
那個木頭也沒有跑掉
The wood just moves up and down in place for a while.
木頭也只是在原地上下動一下子這樣而已
So this is called volatility
所以這個就是所謂的波動
have this up and down movement
有這個上下運動
whatever the reason
不管是什麼原因
as long as you move up
只要你往上一動
air will expand
空氣就會膨脹
will condense into clouds
就會凝結成雲
So all kinds of clouds come out
所以各式各樣不同的雲冒出來
This is a lot of individual convection generation that you saw just now
這是剛才你看的很多個別的對流產生
This is relatively large
這個是比較大支度的
is usually you will see something like this
就是通常你會看到像這種
The whole big cloud
整個一大片的成雲
How much does it rain
成雲多少下的雨
or the light rain in the big rain building
或者大雨樓的小雨
Of course not to say rainstorm
當然不至於說暴雨
It's unlikely
倒是不太可能就是
If there is no wind, will there be clouds?
沒有風會不會有雲
We usually talk about wind and clouds
我們通常都講到風去雲湧
So there must be wind and there must be clouds
所以應該要有風才會有雲
But we used to have one that hurt
可是我們以前這個有一個很疼
the great poet this du fu
偉大的詩人這個杜甫
He has a Qingzhou miscellaneous stone
他這個有一個青州雜石
Generally twenty hands, this is the seventh hand
一般二十手這個裡面第七手
He has a boundless mountain, an isolated city, and a valley
他都有一個茫茫萬叢山孤城山谷間
Wu Fengyun promotes the sun
吳豐雲促晒
If you are unemployed, you will be more critical
不業也越臨關
The two most famous of these are the
其中最有名的這兩句就是這個
Then this unemployed is getting closer
那這個不業越臨關
Then this is astronomical
那這個這是天文的
Leave it to the people at the astronomical institute to explain
留給天文所的人去解釋
A college student from Houhou Earth Institute can also explain
後後地球所這個大學生也可以解釋
then i want to explain
那我想要跟解說
Will no wind and cloud block
無風雲會不會阻塞
If there is no wind, will it
沒有風的話會不會
will the clouds come out
會不會冒雲出來
that's certainly possible
那當然有可能
Because I mentioned it for a long time
因為我剛才也提了半天
It doesn't have to be windy
不用不見得要有風
you can still have clouds
你照樣有可能會有雲
pop up
冒出來
this is for volatility
這就是為了波動
it's just at dusk
這剛好在黃昏的時候
You can see that there are actually many fluctuations in the air
你看到這個空氣中其實它很多波動
Air is like water
空氣其實跟水一樣
same thing
同樣的東西
moving from time to time
不時都在動
What if the air humidity is just right?
你如果空氣這個濕度剛好的話呢
You see just created a cloud
你看剛好造成一朵雲
Usually this tail is invisible
通常這個尾巴是看不到的
because it's usually thin
因為它通常很稀薄
Good luck after giving birth on this day
這一天生育完運氣特別好
The sun just shines from that angle
那太陽剛好從那個一個角度照掛
show you this thin eye
給你看到這個很稀薄的眼睛
So it should be seen that this place is actually a large part of the whole wave
所以應該看到這個地方其實是整個波的一大部分
Just at the place where the height of the wave is the highest, where the wave wind
剛好在這個波的高度最高的地方波風的地方
some clouds will come out
會產生一些雲出來
Why do clouds form where the wind blows?
為什麼會在波風的地方產生雲呢
Because the place where the wave is square is of course where the air rises
因為波方的地方當然是空氣往上升的地方
Usually an ancient place like this is where the air sinks
通常像這種古的地方是空氣往下沉的地方
There are no clouds in most places
多半的地方都是沒有雲
this day is special
這一天是比較特別的
It's more humid
它濕度比較大一點
So there will be clouds even in this place that day
所以那一天連這個地方都會有雲
But this place the clouds are thicker
但是這個地方雲更厚
So this cloud is a cloud produced by fluctuations
所以這種雲是波動產生的雲
it often looks like a lens
它常常看起來像一個透鏡的一樣
So this is called lenticular
所以這個叫透鏡狀
lenticular cloud
透鏡狀的雲
This is really a lenticular cloud
這個就真的是透鏡狀的雲
Sometimes you can see the sky full of clouds like this
有時候你可以看到滿天都是像這種雲
like a lens
就像透鏡一樣
like a thick slice
像厚厚的一片
In fact, this is all generated by waves.
其實這個完全都是波產生的
This is really like playing without wind and clouds
這個真的就像無風雲出賽
you can
你可以
I know it why these two doses learn well
我知道它為什麼這兩劑學得好
In the last section, this somewhat mysterious place
上一節的時候,這個有點神秘的地方
Because it is written in such an unofficial place
因為它是在寫這種官外的地方
It mentions that there is no wind but there are clouds, coming out
它提到說,沒有風可是有雲,冒出來
You feel as if there is no movement, but the enemy suddenly appears
你看覺得好像沒有什麼動靜,可是敵人突然冒出來
There's this air of absurdity coming out of your body
就有這種讓你覺得全身荒謬的氣氛冒出來
You can imagine this place
這個地方你可以想像說這裡面
It seems that your officer is here, then on the opposite side of the mountain or when
好像你的官是在這邊,然後對面山上或者什麼時候
This evil slave's Qibing regiment popped up, no wind and shadow left the fortress
這個兇奴的啟兵團冒出來,無風影出塞
I'm not saying I believe the name of the flying saucer, it may be a so-called flying saucer
我不是說我信那個飛碟叫的,可能是所謂的飛碟
But our dude drinks decently, it's all right
不過我們這位老兄喝的正經,沒事
But this kind of cloud in the broken mirror sometimes looks like this
但是這種就破鏡中的雲,有時候看著就這樣
It seems that suddenly a big tide rises and appears in the sky
好像突然一大潮冒,出現在天空裡
Then this is exactly the relationship that should fluctuate, especially in the mountains
那這完全也就是應該波動的關係,尤其是在山裡面
back then it would have a lot of these fluctuations
那時候它會產生很多這種波動
This kind of fluctuation will produce this kind of cloud if the kind of conditions are just right
這種波動如果這種條件剛好就會產生這種雲
This is often geographical
這種往往有地理性
Certain geographies are particularly prone to such clouds
某些地理它特別容易產生這種雲
so you want to see ufo
所以你想要看飛碟
It looks especially good in that place
它去那個地方看特別好
This is the same lenticular cloud
這也是同樣的透鏡狀的雲
it has several layers
它有個好幾層
It's the same kind of fluctuation not just one layer
它同樣的這種波動不只是一層
sometimes several layers
有時候可以好幾層
Sometimes it looks very, very spectacular
有時候看起來就非常非常的壯觀
This will just go here and look up
這個就會只要到這個往上找
This is actually very, very many
這種其實非常非常的多
Very, very beautiful clouds can be seen
非常非常漂亮的雲都可以看得到
And I just talked for a long time
而且剛才講了半天是講
No weather
無風雲出曬
So if there is no wind
所以這個沒有風的話
Clouds will still come
雲還是會湧
so the wind blows
所以風去雲湧
This is just a general statement
這個只是一般的講法而已
It's okay without the wind
沒有風照樣還可以
that's the other way around now
那現在反過來
If there is wind, do the clouds have to move?
有風的話雲是不是一定要動
After each use, after psychology is disassembled, we may or may not move
各用之後心理學拆開之後,我們大概也可能不會動
It does not move sometimes, why? You can watch this video
那的確是有時候會不動,為什麼呢?你可以看一下這個video
The wind is clearly blowing
風明明在吹喔
But some power supplies don't seem to want to run away
可是有些電源也好像不願意跑掉
Like this teacher here on this mountain
像這位老師在這個山頭這裡
One side is bigger and the other side is small, but it seems that he is not willing to run away
一下邊大一下邊小,但是好像不太願意跑掉
isn't it a bit strange
是不是有點奇怪
So if there is no wind blowing, will the cloud not move? Is it possible to not move?
所以沒有風吹的話,雲會不會不動?會有可能不動嗎?
like this case
就像這種case
The wind is clearly leaving, the wind is blowing
那個風明明離開就是這個風有在吹
But that means I don't want to run away
可是這樣也就是不願意跑掉
is it possible
有可能這樣子嗎
But that's what the movie is about
可是明明這個電影就是這樣講
Actually what's going on
其實講起來是怎麼回事
This is also a wave shadow
這也是波動影這一種
How does this wave shadow come about?
這是怎麼波動影產生呢
Because when the wind blows over the mountain, there are many waves
因為風吹過山的時候就產生很多波
so where the wind blows
所以在波風的地方
cloud is born
雲就產生了
because the air is reborn
因為空氣被往生生
Just when this wave is generated
剛好這個波產生的時候
This wave is called Standing Wave.
這種波叫做Standing Wave這個柱波
when it blows over this mountain
它吹過這個山的時候
The wind of that wave is always in the same place
那個波的風老是在同一個地方
So every time this moisture-laden air
所以每一次這個含有水氣的空氣
As soon as it blows over this mountain
一吹到吹過這個山的時候
in the same place
在同一個地方
it also produces a wind
它同樣產生一個風
where is a wave of wind
一個波的風在哪裡
So the air goes up in that same place
所以空氣在那個同一個地方就往上升
after this wind
過了這個風以後
Air rises down in the same place
空氣在同一個地方往下升
Once it goes down, it rises into the clouds and disappears.
它一旦往下升雲消失掉了
Once it goes up the cloud appears
它一旦往上升雲出現了
So in fact that cloud is not the original cloud
所以實際上那個雲早就不是原來的雲
That cloud is different from that water vapor
那個雲早是不同的那個水蒸氣
If you make a mark for each of the water vapor, say
你如果把那個水蒸氣每一個都做一個記號說
This water vapor is fake and this is mobile
這個水蒸氣是假的這個是移
I don't know where the water vapor in that Chiayi bottle went.
那個嘉義瓶那個水蒸氣早就不知道跑到哪裡去了
But it looks like you're talking about the same cloud
可是看起來你會覺得說好像同一種雲
that's just an illusion
那只是一種假象
In fact, all clouds are illusions
其實所有的雲都是假象
When talking about age, everyone is actually an illusion
說的年齡的時候其實人人都是假象
So in biologists say
所以在生物學家說
Our cells seem to be replaced every seven years.
我們這個細胞好像七年就要換一次
So every seven years I am actually a different person
所以每七年我這個人其實已經是不一樣的人
So I used to say that the American one
所以以前說以前那個美國那個
A swap called that Simpson
一個換罪叫那個Simpson
Oggy Simpson he all scrubs his wife
Oggy Simpson他都磨砂了他的太太
if in case he is convicted
如果萬一他被判罪的話
He can be hidden for seven years and then run out
他可以七年被躲了七年以後再跑出來
say I'm different
說我已經不一樣了
I'm not the original one
我已經不是原來那個
At critical times, I can say that what I want to judge is not
我關鍵時候可以說我要判的不是
not your body
不是你的肉體
It's who you are, who you are as Oggy Simpson
而是你的身份,你的身份就是Oggy Simpson
But the cloud really isn't it's not a solid thing
不過雲的確不是它不是一個固體的東西
So the components inside him are actually changing all the time.
所以它那個裡面的組成成份其實隨時都在改變
The cloud you'll see isn't really a constant thing
你所會看到的雲並不是真正的一個不變的東西
The thing itself is always changing
它那個東西本身是一直在改變
What you see doesn't change is the shape of that thing
你所看到沒有改變的只是形狀那個東西
just a pattern, a form
只是一個pattern,一個形式
You always think that thing, this cloud is not
你一直認定那個東西,這隻雲其實不是
That's just the form of that cloud
那只是那個雲的形式而已
So this thing is a very important point to understand the movement of clouds
所以這個東西是了解雲的運動一個很重要的一點
So the following pattern is also such a phenomenon
所以下面這個pattern也是這樣的這種現象
The water vapor has already been
那個水蒸氣其實早就已經
You can see that the cloud doesn't seem to go anywhere else.
你看覺得這個雲好像沒有跑到別的地方
It's just been moving up and down, but it's not
一直在上下下動而已,其實沒有
That cloud has already gone away
那個雲早就跑掉了
I don't know where the water went
那些水早就不知道跑到哪裡去了
What you see is actually a completely different cloud
你看到的其實完全都是不一樣的雲
That water vapor is already new water vapor
那些水蒸氣都是已經新來的水蒸氣
For the same reason, when you watch the sign reports on TV, you can see
同樣的道理 大家看電視上面的跡象報告的時候看到
Where does a certain typhoon come from?
某個颱風從什麼地方移來
A huge cloud, like a whirlpool, and move here
豪大一團雲 漩渦一樣 然後移到這裡
That's just the form of the vortex running
那只是那個漩渦的形式在跑而已
I don't know where the water went
原來那些水早就不知道到哪裡去了
Those waters have already finished raining
那些水早就下完雨了
There is new water coming out
又有新的水冒出來
It's just that the water runs into the same whirlpool all day long
只是那個水一天到晚都跑到同樣的漩渦裡面
so it looks like
所以看起來好像都
The clouds seem to have the same shape
那個雲好像形狀都一樣
In fact, the water in those clouds has already been replaced with a lot of new ones.
其實那些雲的水早就已經換了很多新的
completely different
完全都不一樣
so the point is
所以這一點是
One of the things you need to know when looking at the cloud
對看雲的時候需要了解的一個
OK, just now we mentioned that the vertical movement is mainly related to the generation of clouds
OK 剛才我們提到說垂直運動主要是產生雲的關係
Then let's say the level will not
那我們說水平會不會
Did you guess wrong about the level?
大家有沒有猜錯 水平的話
because there is no change in air pressure
因為沒有什麼氣壓的改變
So the possibility of creating a cloud
所以造成雲的可能性
doesn't seem too big
好像不是太大
Is there any objection to this
這是有沒有人提出反對的意見
Is there any objection? No one seems to object. Strange
有沒有反對 好像沒有人反對 奇怪
Everyone agrees very much today
大家今天非常agree
In fact, a horizontal pass can also cause clouds
其實水平一通也會造成雲
have you seen this
有沒有看過這種
If you go to the show of this plane
你如果去看這個飛機的表演
Panel sometimes sees that the aircraft performance is very slow
Panel有時候看到飛機體現很慢
when suddenly it's fast
突然它很快的時候
Suddenly, as soon as I dodged and won, I was captured in a certain place on the plane
突然一躲贏就在飛機某個地方整個照住
This is a positive wave
這是一種正波音
Why is it called Zhengbo
它為什麼叫正波音
Because it's generated in exactly the same place as the so-called positive wave wind
因為它產生的地方剛好跟所謂的正波的風一樣
Sharkfron
Sharkfron
It is exactly the same shape as its positive wave
剛好跟它那個正波風的形狀一模一樣
and this place is
而且這個地方就是
When an aircraft accelerates to just supersonic speed
一個飛機加速到剛好要超音速的時候
That's when this cloud was born
那個時候這種雲就產生了
this is weird
這個就很奇怪
How did this cloud come about
怎麼會產生這種雲
The two elements of the cloud we just talked about
我們剛才講的雲的兩大要素
one is water vapor
一個是水中氣
one is saturated
一個是飽和
so you have a way to saturate it
所以你才有辦法讓它達到飽和
In fact, both horizontal and vertical
其實水平垂直都可以啦
it doesn't matter
沒有關係啦
So this horizontal movement
所以這種水平運動
How can it be saturated?
怎麼會使它產生達到飽和呢
When an aircraft accelerates beyond the factor
當一個飛機加速到超過因素的時候
For a while because of the movement of the plane itself
那一陣子因為它飛機本身的運動
faster than its rising wave
比它那個升波還要快
the one with its air
它空氣的那個
The air originally had a rising wave, the so-called compression wave
空氣本來那個升波所謂的壓縮波
when you generate this
當你產生這個時候
your wave source
你的那個波源
When the speed of this wave is faster than yours
比你這個波的速度還要快的時候
the wave generated at that time
那個時候產生的波
That's no ordinary rising wave
那個就不是普通的升波
that's a positive wave
那是正波
That positive wave causes the air to expand dramatically
那種正波會使空氣急劇的膨脹
Usually the rising wave and the expansion are very small
通常那種升波那種膨脹幅度很小
But this positive wave suddenly
可是這種正波它一下子
In a very short time it swells very much
很短的時間它就膨脹得非常厲害
As long as the air expands
空氣只要一膨脹
right away
馬上就能
Rapid expansion produces rapid cooling
急速的膨脹產生急速的冷卻
If you were this
如果你當時的這個
If the moisture content is sufficient
水氣含量夠的話
so rapidly expanding
那麼急速膨脹
let it happen now
馬上就讓它產生
big ticket cloud
一大票雲
His shape is exactly the same as the shape of the positive wave
他的形狀就是剛好跟正波的形狀一模一樣
So this quantity is the so-called positive wave
所以這個量就是所謂的正波
So he this if he keeps going at this supersonic speed
所以他這個如果他一直以這種超音速會的話
That Yun Changchang has been following him
那個雲長長一直跟著他
Because he looked like he hung up a pilot
因為他看他好像掛了一個什麼領機一樣
It's like running for a long time
就是長長在跑這樣子
Sometimes you fly over that drier place
有時候你飛過那個比較乾的地方
the cloud disappears
那個雲就消失掉
The certifier is about to emerge
規證者要冒出來
you say watch that kind of movie
你說看那種電影的話
And he sometimes does not practice local
而且他有時候不執業地方
Sometimes there are two different places
有時候還有兩個不同的地方
As long as that place exceeded the speed of sound at that time
只要那個地方在當時超過音速的話
you will see this cloud
你就會看到這種雲
So the same positive wave cloud
所以同樣的這種正波雲
so this is horizontal movement
所以這是水平運動
accounting is fair
會計是會平的
Is there anything other than this word?
除這個字外還有沒有
This positive wave supersonic
這種正波超音速
Is there anyone climbing here?
這邊有沒有人登山呢
does anyone like mountain climbing
有沒有人喜歡登山
Has anyone seen this cloud before?
有没有人看过这种云呢
In fact, Yushan sometimes has this kind of cloud
其实玉山有时候会有这种云
This is Benechal and this is Qi Yun
这叫Benechal 这个是祁云
because it will be like a Qizi
因为它会像一个祁子一样
Usually this cloud is where it's downwind
通常这种云就是它在下风
Especially an isolated mountain like this
尤其是一个孤立的这种山风
particularly likely
特别有可能
As long as this mountain is not too long
这个山只要不是太长的
like a ridge
像一个岭一样
as long as it is relatively isolated
它只要是比较孤立
and there are no other mountains nearby
而且旁边没有其他的山
block until it has a high probability of producing this cloud
挡住到它产生这种云的可能性很大
like the world's tallest everest
像世界最高峰的Everest
Also often have this kind of Benechal
也常常有这种Benechal
generate this cloud
产生这种云
If you are climbing
你如果是登山的话
you see this cloud
你看到这种云
you plan not to go up
你最打算不要上去
better
比较好一点
why
为什么呢
because when you see this cloud
因为你看到这种云的时候
it means the weather is not going to be good
它代表天气状况不会太好
at least the wind will be strong
至少风会很大
so you were climbing
所以你那个时候登山
can be quite dangerous
可能会蛮危险的
especially the mountain
尤其是那种高山
That mountain wind is so strong
那高山风那么大
but how did it come about
但是怎麼產生的
Because usually you want enough wind speed
因為通常是你要足夠的這種風速
windy enough
風夠大
Of course there is enough water
當然水氣也要夠
when the wind is strong enough
風夠大的時候
when you blow through a main obstacle
當你吹過一個主礙物的時候
in front of the obstacle
在障礙物的前面
it is a high pressure area
它是一個高壓區
But behind this obstacle
可是在這個障礙物的後面
is a low pressure area
是一個低壓區
So of course when an air goes from high pressure to low pressure
所以一個空氣當然從高壓到低壓的時候
it also swells
它也會膨脹
it would have been denser
它本來是比較密
Once in this low pressure area it has no limit
一到這個低壓區它沒有限制
as the air rises
跟空氣往上升一樣
At this time, the air will also expand
這個時候空氣也會膨脹
when the air expands
當空氣膨脹以後
it will cool down
它照樣會冷卻
possible after cooling
冷卻以後就有可能
saturate the water with air
使得水中氣也達到飽和
So you have this cloud
所以你就會產生這個起雲
Of course there are one or two other causes of cloud formation
當然起雲的成因還有其他一兩個
But the most important cause
不過最重要的成因
It's because of the wind inside
就是因為裡面有這個風
so why do you see clouds
所以你為什麼看到起雲
Almost every time
每一次都幾乎就是這種
just behind this mountain
剛好在這個山後面
just one
就是一個
like a cloud floating in the ocean
好像一個起雲在飄洋一樣
the reason for it
它的原因呢
That's it
就是這樣
so this is another
所以這是另外一個
Similarly, Ma Dehong in Switzerland is particularly easy to produce
同樣這個瑞士這個馬德虹特別容易產生
Because he is a particularly isolated mountain
因為他特別孤立的一個山峰
So he often has a big flag
所以他常常有一個一面大旗一樣
hanging on his flagpole
就掛在他的旗桿上面
it will
這是會的
So while horizontal motion is not the most important cause of clouds
所以雖然水平運動不是產生雲的最重要原因
But he can also generate clouds
但是他也可以產生雲
Just gave two examples
剛才舉了兩個例子
OK
OK
So we conclude that the shape of the cloud is mainly due to the flow of air
所以我們總結雲的外形主要是空氣在流動
Clouds are formed in the air
而雲是在空氣裡面成型
If the air flow pattern does not change
如果空氣流動形式不變
The shape of the cloud will not change
雲的形狀也不會變
look at those wave shadows
你看看那些波動影
it stays that way
它保持那個樣子
Why? Because the shape of the air flow will not change
為什麼?因為空氣流動的形狀都不會變
And if the air flows in the wrong way
而且如果空氣流動的那種形式不當不變
and not moving
而且不動
Instant air is moving
即使空氣在流動
the cloud doesn't move
那個雲也不動
Because the cloud is in this form only
因為雲是在這種形式而已
The cloud of the cloud actually represents the kind of
雲的雲其實是代表那種
a pattern
一種pattern
So the wind blows that cloud whatever you want
所以風隨便你怎麼吹那個雲
It's not moving at all
根本就還聽在那裡不動
This is the most important point of watching the movement of clouds
這就是雲的 看雲的運動的最重要的一點
OK, come on down, we usually say that clouds condense when they reach saturation.
OK 再來下來 我們通常說雲達到飽和就凝結
Right or wrong because common sense doesn't seem to be wrong
對還是錯 因為一般常識來講好像是沒有什麼錯
But seriously, it's not quite right.
但其實認真來看其實不太對
Because the so-called so-called saturation is 100%
因為所謂的一般所謂的飽和就是百分之百
Relatively moderate and you can reach saturation
相對適度你就有達到飽和
The so-called relative moderate is under a specific temperature and pressure
所謂的相對適度就是在特定的溫度氣壓之下
Ratio of current steam to saturated steam
當前的蒸汽跟飽和蒸汽的比值
that is called relative moderation
那個叫做相對適度
Saturated steam is generally determined by temperature
飽和蒸汽一般來講是因為溫度來決定
under a certain temperature
在一定的溫度之下
This steam that needs to be balanced on your level
你水平面上所需要平衡的這種蒸汽
That is called saturated steam
那個叫飽和蒸汽
British scientist Teklin Kelvin
英國的科學家特克林凱爾文
he proposes a
他提出一個
He proves to you that when your relative numbers are hundreds of words
他跟你證明說當你的相對數字百字百的時候
I will give you a drop of water, I promise that the drop of water must be multiplied
我給你一個水滴,我保證那個水滴一定要增化掉
And it must be multiplied until all of them disappear, do you want to believe it or not
而且一定要增化到全部消失掉,你想不相信
We usually say that I don't believe it, we have already said in textbooks
我們通常人說我才不相信,我們已經課本上講說
Humidity is 100 words, it is starting to be lingering, but CAMMAN says it is wrong
濕度百字百就是開始要凌結,結果CAMMAN說不對
Humidity, the water droplet should be increased, I didn't believe it at the beginning
濕度百字百這個水滴應該增化掉,我當初也不相信
But when you go to the partner company, it seems that you don't have a big face
可是你去搭檔公司,好像都沒有大臉
Later, many people did a lot of experiments, and it is indeed the case
後來很多人做了很多實驗,的確也是這樣
Indeed, it is indeed multiplied, and I later found out that our ordinary water droplets
的確真的是增化掉,後來才知道說我們一般的水滴
That's a few different kinds of water droplets, our normal water droplets
那是幾種不同的水滴,我們一般的水滴
It's not clean enough at all, if the water droplet is clean
根本就是不夠乾淨,你如果那個水滴很乾淨的話
The water droplet of your relative number of hundreds of characters will increase and dissolve
你那個百字百的相對數字那個水滴會增化掉
This has been proved by many experiments
這個已經是很多實驗證明過
Then under what circumstances that water drop
那在什麼情況之下那個水滴
won't multiply
不會增化掉
The water drops will get off, there must be something else
水滴會沾掉 要有別的東西
not just water
不是只有水而已
Many experiments have proved that
很多實驗的就是證明出來了
just below our surface environment
就是在我們地表的環境之下
if you only have water vapor
你如果只有水蒸氣
nothing else the air will stick
沒有別的東西 空氣會沾掉
you smoked it very clean
你把它抽得非常乾淨
Use a filter to get it very clean
用過濾的東西把它濾得非常乾淨
Are you probably 300% or 400% relatively
你大概相對是300% 還是400%
you will have to condense out
你才會有凝結出來
Otherwise there would be no condensation
要不然的話是不會有凝結
Usually our air is not so clean
通常我們空氣都不會那麼乾淨
There's a lot of stuff in there
裡面都一大堆東西
a bunch of these little particles
一大堆這種小粒子
That kind of small particle is the so-called condensation here
那種小粒子就是這邊所謂的凝結
Usually you need the help of these little particles
通常你要這種小粒子的幫忙
Water vapor can only be used when the relative number is 100%.
水蒸氣才有辦法在相對數字百分之百的時候
just started to condense
才開始凝結
Otherwise it would be so-called oversatisfaction
要不然的話它會所謂的過飽
it will go all the way to 300 400
它會一直到300 400
Then it starts to condense into water
然後才開始凝結成水
So this is called condensation
所以這個就是所謂的凝結
So it's important to say
所以很要緊的一點就是說
Clouds will form in our air
在我們空氣裡面要形成雲
almost certain to have this condensation
幾乎一定要有這種的凝結
Otherwise there would be no clouds
要不然是不會有雲
Very clean air and probably no clouds
非常乾淨的空氣大概也不會有雲
So it must be clean without air
所以不要有空氣就一定很乾淨
There must be some fine dust in the air
空氣一定有這些細小的一些灰塵
Some dust particles create this cloud
一些微塵產生這種雲
So this thing is called condensation nuclei
所以這東西叫做凝結核
The most common condensation nuclei are
最通常的凝結核就是
Leuphane-Anderlein
Leuphane-Anderlein
This Sodium Ammonium Sulphate
這個Sodium Ammonium Sulphate
And the usual severity
還有普通的這種嚴厲
Ordinary is less severe
普通嚴厲比較少一點
Most of this flow cream
最多的這種流霜
if the cloud continues to grow
雲繼續長大的話
will turn into rain
會變成雨
become raindrops
變成雨滴
I used Google to find some cartoonists
我這個用那個Google去找了一些漫畫家
raindrops have any opinion
雨滴有什麼意見
Which one of the raindrops do you think is the best?
大家覺得哪一個雨滴畫得最好
or which one is the worst
或者哪一個畫得最爛
In fact, they all look the same
其實看起來每個都一樣的
He must have painted them all the same.
一定他畫得也每個都一樣
But the most important point is that the raindrops here are all drawn wrong
但是最重要的一點就是說這邊雨滴全部都畫錯了
raindrops don't look like that
雨滴不是那個樣子
this is not a raindrop
這個不是雨滴
this is tears
這個是眼淚
This is a teardrop
這個是掉眼淚的淚珠
Raindrops are not like this
雨滴才不是這個樣子
Apparently these cartoonists have never seen raindrops like this
顯然這些漫畫家從來沒有看到雨滴這樣
what raindrops look like
雨滴是什麼樣子
The raindrops are actually quite steep
雨滴其實像蠻陡一樣
You said to use that kind of quick photo
你說用那種快速的照上去
When it rains, take pictures of the raindrops
下雨的時候去拍那個下雨的雨滴
This is an example
這個就是一個例子
Below the raindrops is flat
雨滴下面是平
almost flat
幾乎是平的
sometimes farther
有時候比較遠一點
But most of them are cheaper
但是大部分下面比較便宜一點
farther up
上面比較遠一點
This is the image of real raindrops and this is what it looks like
這是真正的雨滴的形象就是這個樣子
You see, none of the cartoonists came out with a drawing board
你看那個所有的漫畫家沒有一個畫盤頭出來
But if you know slip mechanics
可是你如果知道溜滴力學的話
That's the only thing that's reasonable
就是唯有這個才是合理的
That's exactly what it looks like
的確就是這個樣子
Indeed the image of raindrops
的確雨滴的形象
It's exactly the shape of this barbarian head
完全就是這種蠻頭的形狀
And here's one that we're doing experiments in a wind tunnel
然後這邊有一個是我們在風洞裡面做實驗
You can put a bead of water in a vertical wind tunnel
你可以把一個水珠放在一個垂直的風洞
there's wind blowing up below
下面有風吹上來
You can use this as long as the technology and equipment are in high condition
你可以把這個只要這個技術跟這個設備條件高
You can stop this droplet in the air
你可以把這個水滴停在空中
let it stop there
讓它停在那裡
Even in front of your eyes you can watch it stew for two hours
就算你眼前你可以看它燉它兩個鐘頭
if you want
如果要的話也可以
We did this kind of experiment before I was at this time
那之前我當年這個時候我們就做這種實驗
This one is 1 to 3mm
這個是1到3mm的這種
and no power plant
而且沒有電廠
In addition, there are cases for power plants
另外有做電廠的case
But today I won't have the chance to tell you
不過今天不會有機會跟大家講
This drop of water floating in the air
這個浮在空中的水滴
Do you see if its shape is that of a brute?
你看它形狀是不是蠻頭羊的
blow up
下往上吹
The same is equivalent to this raindrop
同樣的相當於這個雨滴
like falling from above
從上面往下掉一樣
then i make it stop there
那我為了使它停在那裡
adjust from time to time
不時要調節
speed of air
空氣的速度
Because the water droplets will gradually increase in size after a long time.
因為水滴久了它會慢慢增化這樣
so it gets smaller
所以它會變小
So its speed will change
所以它的速度會改變
This one is through a glass pie
這個是隔著一個玻璃派的
Then I want to raise the stage here
那我要這邊提階段
I'll mention it here
那我這邊提
mentioned water of course, but rain if it's high enough
提到當然是水,但是雨如果夠高的話
There is not only water in it, of course there is also ice, that is what will be mentioned below
裡面不只有水當然還有冰,那就是下面要提到的
So that's the water drop that's all in the air in october four
所以就是,十月四裡面的全在空中的水滴
So I hope everyone will go back after watching this today
所以希望今天看完這個以後大家回去
The next time it rains, you have to think about it all over your head, that's right
下一次下雨,滿腦子都要想到滿頭,才對
OK, so when the temperature in that cloud drops below zero degrees Celsius
OK,所以當那個雲中的溫度降到零度C以下的時候
Water vapor and water droplets in clouds may start to freeze into ice
雲中的水蒸氣和水滴可能會開始凍結成冰
Water droplets may freeze into ice, but if water vapor freezes directly
水滴有可能凍結成冰,那水蒸氣如果直接成冰的話
That is a freezing phenomenon called sublimation
那是一種凍結的現象,叫sublimation
This is just common sense, common sense is often not the truth
這個也是只是常識而已,常識往往不是真理
When observing in the clouds
在雲中做觀測的時候
The temperature of its clouds is often minus 20 degrees
它的云的温度常常是零下二十几度
As a result, the water is still low
结果那个水还是水低
The water inside is still low, and it still hasn't turned into ice
里面的水还是水低 还是没有变成冰
That water is too cold
那个水叫过冷水
That supercooled water is often very, very common.
那个过冷水常常都是非常非常平常的现象
So what we often observe below zero is to say
所以我们在零下常常的观察是说
minus ten to twenty degrees
零下十度到二十度
Sometimes even to minus 40 degrees
有时候甚至到零下四十度
it will really turn into ice
它才会真的变成冰
Otherwise it is often still a lot of water
要不然的话它常常还是很多水
and it's bad to say
而且很糟糕的就是说
you know it's water
你知道它是水
But once your plane flies over
可是你飞机一飞过去
it may turn to ice in no time
它可能马上就变成冰
and as soon as it flies past
而且它一飞过去
It's the water that sticks to the wings of your plane
它那个水就黏在你的飞机的翅膀上面
and can't get rid of
而且就甩不掉
And once the cloud is thick enough,
而且你一旦那个云够厚的话
you keep flying
你一直飞
Its ice is getting thicker
它那个冰越来越厚
In the end, the shape of your wings completely changed
最后你那个翅膀形状完全都变样
It's that changed shape, that plane
它那个变样变大那个飞机
won't get up at all
根本就会不起来
Because the wings of an airplane must have a certain shape
因为飞机的翅膀一定要有一定的形状
it can go up
它才可以往上升
When your airplane wings are covered with ice like this
当你这个飞机翅膀结了这种冰的话
you'll come down again
你会再来往下掉
Many plane crashes are due to the phenomenon of aircraft crews
很多飛機失事是因為飛機機兵的現象
The machine is on the paper list
機在紙榜上面
The most serious machine soldier does not mean that the soldier is directly glued to it
最嚴重的機兵不是說那個兵直接黏在上面
but this supercooled water
而是這種過冷水
super cold water
起見是過冷水
But once he touches this solid surface
可是他一旦碰上這個固態的表面的時候
He immediately formed an army
他立刻就結成兵
and can't take it off
而且就拿不掉
he's so clingy
他就黏得非常緊
that is the most dangerous situation
那是最危險的情況
so under what circumstances
所以在什麼情況之下
he will form an army
他會結成兵
same as coagulation
跟凝結合一樣
He wants another thing called a soldier box
他要有另外一個東西叫做兵盒
He can do it only if he gets a soldier
要讓兵盒他才可以
He needs a soldier box before he can form a soldier
他要有兵盒他才可以結成兵
The so-called ordinary weapon box often processes ordinary things
那所謂平常兵盒往往進程普通的東西
just ordinary sand
就是普通的沙土
just ordinary dust
普通的灰塵而已
So you think that this thing should be all over the sky
所以你覺得說那這東西應該滿天都是
not all over the sky
沒有滿天都是
Ordinary sand is actually big
普通的沙子其實很大
Ordinary sand means maybe
普通的沙子就是說也許就是
fraction of a millimeter
一個毫米的幾分之一
You gotta get this thing up that high
你要把這場東西弄到那麼高空
it is not going up
它是上不去
so be slow
所以要很慢
So the high altitude is actually
所以高空的其實
The sky is clean
高空倒是滿乾淨的
so you have these things that condense into ice
所以你要有這些凝結成冰的東西
In fact, it is full
其實是滿少的
But once it freezes
不過它一旦結成冰
it's quite beautiful
它倒是滿漂亮的
You can see many different
你可以看到很多各式各樣不同的
snowflake shape
冰精 雪花的形狀
Here is an example for you
這邊是給大家一個例子
Snowflakes usually mentioned in camp
通常在營餓裡面講的雪花
Many ice spirits collide
很多冰精碰在一起
it combines with each other
它彼此結合起來
become the so-called Goose Feather University
就變成所謂的鵝毛大學
Have you seen Goose Feather University
你有沒有看到鵝毛大學
It's not actually a piece of ice
其實不是一片冰
several different pieces of ice
好幾片不同的冰
even hundreds of pieces of different years up
甚至好幾百片不同的年起來
That is the so-called Goose Feather University
那就是所謂的鵝毛大學
something like this
類似這種情況
this piece
這個一片
In fact, there are probably dozens of different
其實大概有幾十片不同的
The little ice spirits are all connected together
小冰精全部連在一起
caused
所造成
In addition to this ice aid, of course there are also ice explosions
這個冰濟以外當然還有冰爆
bigger stuff
更大的玩意兒
This thing is more dangerous
這個東西就比較危險了
When the ice burst is relatively small
冰爆比較小的時候
We have this called a soft burst
我們有這個叫做軟爆
called Blobber
叫做Blobber
Soft bursts usually occur in very specific shapes
軟爆通常發生很特別的形狀
A bit like our Lianwu
有點像我們這個蓮霧的那種樣子
But it's very small
不過很小啦
Little Lianwu
小蓮霧
The ice bursts are of course big and small
那冰爆當然有大有小
This is 2006
這個是2006年
Some ice blasts in front of my back yard
在我家後院前的一些冰爆
so if you don't know
所以你如果不知道
what kind of steamed stuffed bun is there
有這個什麼包子
pearl balls or something
什麼珍珠丸子之類的
no
不是
This is an ice blast
這個是冰爆
That time the parcel company lost money
那一次這個包裹公司賠了
Lost us 20,000 yuan
賠了我們兩萬塊
fix the roof
修這個屋頂
Because the ice burst
因為這個冰爆下來
Is the roof not pierced?
屋頂會不會是沒有打穿
But there are a lot of cold spots
不過這個凹凍倒是不少
So that time it seemed like this
所以那一次好像這個
The parcel company over there lost money
那邊的包裹公司賠了
throughout the region
整個地區都有
the one in the area
這個地區的那個
The parcel company will pay for it
包裹公司賠的不得了
This is the largest ice storm in the world record in 2010, 0.88 kilograms and 20 centimeters in diameter
這是2010年 目前世界紀錄最大的冰暴 0.88公斤 直徑20公分
It's better not to go out in this weather
那這個天氣最好不要出去
So the clouds represent the possibility of a large ice storm.
所以雲中代表冰暴有可能很大
Under what circumstances will an ice storm occur?
什麼情況之下會產生冰暴
This is all based on such a big
這個都是要基於 那麼大的基於
What conditions do you need to generate such a large ice storm?
你要產生這麼大的冰暴 要有什麼條件
Must have that ascender has very strong
一定要有那個上升器有非常旺盛
Because if the ascender is not strong enough
因為如果上升器有不夠旺盛
That thing condensed a little bit and fell off.
那個東西根本凝結了一點點就掉下來
So it has to be so strong that it goes all the way up
所以它一定要非常強 強到它一直往上
Then collide with others, grow bigger and longer
然後跟別的碰在一起 越長越大越長
up to or even higher than that too high for an ice storm
達到甚至比那個太高的冰暴
The typhoon is even faster
颱風速度還要大
when it goes up all the way up to
它一直往上升的時候升到
About 60 to 70 meters per second
每秒大概六七十公尺
so fast ascent
那麼快的上升速度
to produce such a large ice storm
才能產生這麼大的冰暴
Then once your ascending current is not enough to support it
那一旦你在上升界流不夠支撐它的時候
it just started to fall
它才開始往下掉
So when you see such a big ice storm
所以你一看到這麼大的冰暴
This represents the original
這代表那個原裡面
the speed is very very high
速度是非常非常的高
So a whole bunch of this process
所以一大堆的這種過程
how do we study it
我們要怎麼來研究它
Of course, the most direct way is to
當然最直接辦法就是
Will go to the operator to observe
會到營運員去觀測
But I will go to the operator to observe it.
可是會到營運員去觀測那不得了
The first consumption will be very large
第一耗會非常之大
The second is very dangerous
第二是非常危險
Generally speaking
一般就是說
real worst area
真正的最嚴重的地區
Most likely, they just dare not go in.
大概一般會就是不敢進去
dare not drive in
不敢開進去
Some people go in by accident
有的人進去那是不小心進去
If you accidentally go in, it's a serious situation.
不小心進去那個情況嚴重
lots of fighting chances to go in
很多戰鬥機會進去
will be beaten by ice
會被冰暴打的
There's something wrong with the windows too
窗子也出了問題
The shape of the wings has also changed
這個翅膀形狀也變了
a lot of boil
一大堆熬動
We generally have another method theory
我們一般另外一種方法學說
all the physical processes we know
把我們所知道的一切物理過程
represented by mathematical formulas
通通用數學式子來代表
This is called a mathematical formula
這叫數學式子通通都是
The obtained partial text is represented by replacing it with
所得偏文用換成來代表
Then formulate its initial boundary conditions
然後制定它的初始邊界條件
Use a computer to find a set of solutions
用電腦去求出一組解出來
Then answer these
然後把這些解答
Draw it with the method of computer drawing
用電腦畫圖的方法把它畫出來
I can come and explain what the process is like
我可以來了解說這個過程到底是怎麼樣
If compared with the actual observation
如果跟實際觀測比較
if it's good
如果是不錯的話
We can take this cloud model
我們可以把這個雲模式
The help produced is a research tool
所製造出來的幫助是一種研究工具
can come to study
可以來研究說
The formation of a cloud is roughly like its internal structure
雲的形成跟它的內部的結構大致這樣
So this is one of our institutes
所以這個是一個我們研究所
Made a cloud model like this
所做的一個雲模式這樣
make a cloud make a base cloud
做一個雲 做一個基雲
Its pattern basically at least looks like
它的模式基本上至少外觀滿像
Kiyun starts from the ground
基雲從地面開始
grow to protrude a little
長到還凸過來一點
And then as soon as you get to this really long, real inflammation
然後一到對這種很長的這種真狀炎
in this flat city
在這個平流城
Produced at the top of this convective city
在這個對流城的頂部生產
So this is an example of a fish pattern
所以這是一個魚模式的一個例子
you can see this
你可以看到這個
Indeed compared with the real observation
的確跟真正觀測比較
It is indeed full of images
的確是滿像的
So this once this after
所以這個一旦這個之後
We can put all kinds of different fish inside the fish
我們可以把魚裡面各種不同的魚
ice burst cloud low ice crystals
冰爆 雲低 冰晶
Draw different windcloths
把不同的風布畫出來
and then animate it too
然後也做成動畫
You can know where the ice burst and where
你就可以知道什麼地方下冰爆什麼地方
It can be predicted that
可以做預測就是
The blue above is all ice
上面這個藍色的全部都是冰
The red part, the ice burst part
紅色的部分 冰爆的部分
The green part represents the part where it rains
綠色的部分代表下雨的部分
at this time
這個時候
We use it as a research tool
我們把它當作一種研究的工具來使用
It's still very useful
它還滿好用的
And if you want that kind of thing, you can study it.
而且要那種東西可以來研究說
how big is the flood
洪水到底有多大
How much rain can you have with one fortune
你一個基運可以下多少雨
Do you want to guess
大家要不要猜一下
How much rain can an ordinary lucky flower bring
一朵普通的基運它可以下多少雨
How many tons can be dropped
可以下多少萬噸
do you want to guess
要不要猜一下
10,000 tons seems to be asking for a price
一萬噸好像在喊價一樣
100,000 tons, 1,000,000 tons
十萬噸一百萬噸
almost one million tons
差不多一百萬噸
even millions of tons
甚至幾百萬噸
a simple luck
一朵簡單的基運
so much water can come out
就可以下那麼多的水出來
Anyway very very strong
總之非常非常強
Speaking of the flood means
講到洪水就是說
I just talked about a multiple choice question
剛才講到一個選擇題
Everyone, be brave and choose
大家要勇敢一點選擇一下
Which flood was the largest ever to occur on earth
哪一個洪水是地球上發生過最大的
One is the time when Datong water was in the age of shaking
一個是地搖時代大一致水那一次
The second is Deep Gold as mentioned above
第二個是深金上面講
Noah's Ark
諾亞方舟
The so-called Great Ark of Animal Rescue conveys
所謂的動物的救大方舟傳達
That time, it might have been Typhoon Morakot.
那一次或者是莫拉克颱風千里零零的
i bring soda with this
我把汽水帶這個
you probably don't know
您親的大概不太知道
Your older self remembers having this big bottle of soda in this
您自己大一點的還記得有這個很大的把汽水在這個
The fifth answer is to fly above the knot
第五個答案是以上節飛
we have some experts here
我們這邊有一些專家
The real biggest flood is not long after the formation of the ninth hill
真正最大洪水是第九岡形成不久了以後
That time was really the biggest
那一次才是真的最大的
because why
因為為什麼
Now the flood is once
現在洪水一次都是
For example, if you are given tens of millions of tons of water
譬如說給你一千萬噸幾千萬噸的水
but what was that time
可是那一次呢是什麼
That rain caused the entire ocean
那一次的下雨造成整個海洋
You don't have that much water now
你現在不會那麼大的水
Not so much water now
現在不會那麼大的水
Because when our earth first started
因為我們地球剛開始的時候
There was no water for a while
剛有一陣子是沒有水
Later, a lot of water vapor is slowly released from the earth's crust.
後來從地殼裡面慢慢釋放很多水蒸氣出來
Then it starts to create a lot of geo
然後就開始造成很多的地緣
So it's not the same as silver now
所以說現在跟銀不太一樣
Silver must have been dazzling back then
那時候銀一定很耀眼
full of dark clouds
滿天烏雲
water vapor everywhere
到處都是水氣
hot everywhere
到處都是熱騰騰
volcanoes everywhere
到處都是火山
that steam comes out
那種水氣出來
not ordinary so-called silver
不是普通的所謂的銀
that was a volcanic eruption
那是火山爆發
volcanic eruptions
火山爆發
Even in the current volcanic eruption
即使現在的火山爆發裡面
largest part
最大部分
The released gas is still water vapor
放出來的氣體還是水中氣
mostly water vapor
大部分都是水中氣
Second is carbon dioxide
其次才是二氧化碳
sulfur dioxide
二氧化硫
and then finally
然後最後才是
it's bomb now
現在是彈
So I was still an old demon at the time.
所以彈當時還算是一個老妖人
The most common gas is this
最多的氣體其實是這種
For a while, the earth actually had many of these
地球有一陣子其實很多這種
But because of the environment of the earth
可是因為地球的環境
a little cold
冷了一點
So the water will become clean soon
所以水中氣不久它就凌潔
So this kind of process has been going through I don't know how long
所以這種過程一直經歷了不知道多久
Finally, all the excess water and air in it are all in the early morning water.
終於把所有裡面過剩的水中氣全部都凌晨水
really biggest biggest flood
真正最大最大的洪水
This is how the world's oceans are now created
現在世界的海洋就是這樣造成
this is what is called
這個就是所謂的
The biggest flood ever happened, so you guessed it
最大的洪水產生了,所以你猜這個
Of course he doesn't know that he can't guess
當然他不是猜不來就知道
Ok, what impact does the cloud have on the overall environment?
Ok,雲對全體環境有什麼影響?
I'm not saying that the cloud is only good-looking over there.
雲我講不會只在那邊好看而已
There must be some effect on the entire atmospheric environment
對整個大氣環境一定會有某種作用
What is his role like?
他所扮演的角色是怎麼樣?
The first everyone knows this so-called
第一個大家知道這個所謂
A star fish is not a fish, it nourishes all things
星魚不魚,滋潤萬物
this
這個
The squid place is of course on the ground
魷魚的地方當然這個地面上展著
crops are fine
作物就好
no if not
沒有的話就不行
this is that
這個是那個
NASA this Modus
NASA這個Modus
made this surface color
所做的這種地表顏色
real color
真正顏色
Overview of
的概況
you can tell by saying
你可以看出來說
some places
有的地方
high humidity
濕度大
looks green
看起來就綠
The surface has some straight backs
地表有一些直背
where the color looks dry and cool of course
這個顏色看起來乾酷的地方當然
It's just sprinkled in the desert
就是水灑 沙漠地带
Like a salad in the west of China
像沙拉 中国的西部
and central australia
还有澳大利亚的中部
It's all desert
这全部都是沙漠地带
So this role needs to be adjusted
所以这个作用大家要调整
What is the second fish for?
第二个鱼是干嘛
Is the most efficient cleaner of the atmosphere
是大气最有效率的清洗工
inside our atmosphere
我们的大气里面
If there is no such process of rain
如果没有这种下雨的过程的话
Our pollution has been accumulating and accumulating
我们这个污染东西一直累积一直累积
just stop
就是不停
it won't be cleared
它就不会被清除掉
that clearing effect
那这种清除作用
The strongest effect is this rain
最强的作用就是这种下雨
This is the mechanism of heavy rain and rain
这是沉雨雨跟降雨的机制
The mechanism of Shen Yuyu is the biggest
那沉雨雨的机制最大
the most efficient
里面最有效率的
It is the so-called sinking rain effect
就是所谓的沉雨雨作用
Didn't we just talk about Ling Jiehe?
我们刚才不是讲凌洁河吗
You only need a Lingjiehe
你只要有一个凌洁河
It is possible to absorb this moisture
它就有可能吸附这个水气
Then a cloud or raindrop is formed
然后就形成一个云或者雨滴
As long as you are in the rainy process
只要你这个沉雨雨的过程的话
Then your thing and the river
那你这个东西连带这个河
Even in this rain everything falls to the ground
連在這個雨的全部都掉到地面
so the air is clean
所以空氣就乾淨了
so why after it rains
所以為什麼下雨以後
The air seems to be cleaner
空氣好像看起來比較乾淨
Or the air looks cleaner after it snows
或者下雪以後空氣看起來也比較乾淨
It is because of this process of rain
就是因為這個成雨的過程
Sweep away these polluting things in the air
掃除了這個空氣中這些污染的東西
This is an experiment done by others
這個是人家做的實驗
The representative said that after it snows
這個代表說這個下雪的以後
Indeed, I saw a circle around the snow
的確在這個雪的周圍裡看到一圈
This sweat, this dirt
這個汗渣的這種污塵
was brought down by this snow
就被這個雪帶下來
it means
這代表說
it does have a good cleaning effect
它的確有很好的這種清除作用
There is another very expensive thing over here
那這邊還有一個很調貴的東西
This thing is called Gridfield Gap
這個東西叫Gridfield Gap
snow or rain
下雪或者下雨
When the particle is very small
在這個粒子很小的時候
it clears well
它清除得很好
It clears well when the particles are large
粒子很大的時候它清得很好
But when the particle is between 0.1 and 1 as the surface
可是當粒子在0.1到1個為面
It can hardly be cleared, and it can be cleared very little
它幾乎清不掉,它能清的就很少
So there's always these 0.1 to 1 millimeters in the air
所以空氣中老是有這些0.1到1左右的毫米
A thing of this great concentration
這個很大的一個濃度的一個東西
That thing is almost impossible to clear
那個東西就幾乎清不掉
That seems like how you wash it those particles
那個好像你怎麼衝刷它那些粒子
always in the air
老是在空中
there's a physical reason for that
那這有一個物理原因
we used to do
以前我們曾經做過
A calculation model we made
我們做的一個計算模式
calculated result
計算出來的結果
That's exactly what it looks like
的確就是這個樣子
The middle one is called Griffel Gammel
中間這個叫Griffel Gammel
This guy Griffel when he first brought it up
這個人Griffel他第一個提出來的時候
there is such a possibility
有這種可能性
Then we have confirmed that this phenomenon does exist.
那我們是證實說的確有這個現象
ok
ok
So this third character is
所以這第三個角色是
Clouds affect the Earth's ambient light
雲會影響地球的這個環照率
The so-called ambient light ratio is Albido
所謂的環照率就是Albido
that of course means
那當然就是說
If you look at something in space
假如你在太空中看某一個東西
how bright
有多亮
In fact, if that thing doesn't light up by itself
其實如果那個東西不是自己化亮
It's the kind that inverts the color of other light sources
而是反色別的光源而來的那種
That brightness is the so-called slowing force
那個亮度就是所謂的緩造力
So the greater the retardation
所以緩造力越大
Indicates that those things may be brighter
表示那些東西可能越亮
In terms of the celestial body
那在天體裡面來講
inside our celestial body
我們天體裡面
The brightest in the sky are of course the sun and the moon
天空裡面最亮當然就是太陽跟月亮
The two largest
這兩個最大
Of course the sun brightens itself
太陽當然是自己化亮
Of course the moon is illuminated by the sun
月亮當然是被太陽照
besides these two
除了這兩個之外
Which is the brightest celestial body
最亮的天體是哪一個
Venus
金星
Has anyone voted for Mars?
有沒有人投火星的票
No
沒有
strangeness
奇怪
all Venus fans
都是金星迷
But it is true
不過的確
Venus is nothing but the sun and the moon
金星是除了太陽月亮以外
third
第三
third two
第三兩
is auric
是金常性的
why is venus so bright
金星為什麼那麼亮
these two reasons
這兩個原因
because it's close
因為它很近
first because it's close
第一個因為它很近
it's closer to us
它比較靠近我們
so this is the first reason
所以這是第一個原因
The first reason is because it is surrounded by a very dense cloud
第一個原因是因為它被一整很密的雲包圍
What about his clouds, unlike our place where there are no clouds?
他的云呢 不像我们这个地方有的云没有云
He surrounded all the ninety or so secret clouds
他把这九十几都是秘密的云全部都包围了
But his cloud is a bad cloud
可是他的云那是很糟糕的云
His clouds are all acid, all are clouds of acid
他的云都是流酸的 全部都是流酸的云
So this is bad because Jingxing is called Vinus on the Western side
所以这个很糟糕 因为京兴这个西洋那边叫Vinus
Weiner is a very cute girl
维纳是很可爱的一个女生
But in fact, Jingxing is a very bad place
可是实际上京兴是一个很糟糕的地方
His clouds are all acid, all clouds of acid
他的云全部都是流酸 都是流酸的云
His ground is more than 400 degrees
他的地面是四百多度
That's terrible. He's just hot medicine.
那是不得了 他根本就是热的药品
As soon as all the water gets there, it doesn’t just boil, it literally melts away.
那个所有的水一到那边马上不只是沸腾 根本就真化掉了
His pressure is more than ninety times that of the earth's surface
他的压力是九十几 就是地球表面的九十几倍
So if you're not protected, you can't breathe at all.
所以你如果不是保护的话 你根本就不能呼吸了
It's as if you are shallow in this sea, about 2,000 meters under pressure
好像你被浅在这个海里面 大概两千公尺左右的压力一样
So much pressure, this is Jingxing's surface
那么大的压力 这是京兴的表面
Bi Xing looks so bright, but there is nothing to envy
畢星看起來那麼亮其實沒有什麼好羨慕的
That's because it was blown out whole by a secret cloud
那是因為它被秘密的一層雲整個爆出了
So it reflects this sunlight very, very strongly
所以它反射這個太陽光非常非常的強烈
It looks very bright in the night sky
看起來在晚上的空中看起來非常亮
Earth is not so much
地球就沒有那麼多
Earth's albedo is not as strong
地球的反照率就沒有那麼強
So the blue part of the earth basically sees the sea surface
所以地球藍色的部位基本上是看到海面的
The surface of the sea is very dark if you look directly at it.
海面的話如果直接看的話那是非常暗
What is the reason for the reflection of the earth?
那地球的反照是因為什麼
Mostly because the cloud doesn't matter
主要是因為雲沒關係
cloud it is very white
雲它非常白
So when the sun shines on it, it reflects back
所以太陽一照它給它反射回去
The Earth includes clouds including floor albedo
那地球包括雲包括地板反射率
The reflection band is about 30%
反射帶大概30%
So the albedo is 0.3%
所以反照率0.3%
This is our common sense of the earth's albedo
這是我們一般常識上的地球反照率
If cloud cover on Earth increases
如果地球上的雲量增加的話
The albedo of the earth will increase
那地球的反照率會增加
Because there are more clouds
因為雲多了嘛
When there are more clouds, its albedo will increase
雲多了以後它的反照率會增加
if you were an alien
假如你是一個外星人的話
Because the earth is a little suddenly bright
因為地球有點突然亮
The biggest possible reason is that the earth's clouds suddenly increased
最大的可能原因就是地球的雲突然增多了
then say your next question
那時候就說你下一個問題
Why do Earth's clouds increase?
為什麼地球的雲會增多
he started researching
他就開始研究
There are of course various reasons for this
這個當然各式各樣的原因
next one
再接下來一個
What is the most important greenhouse atmosphere on Earth
什麼是地球上最重要的溫室氣氛
If you don't know a little bit, it will change
如果不知道一點講都會改化
right
對不對
The most important thing is actually water vapor
最重要的其實是水蒸氣
Water vapor is the largest greenhouse atmosphere on Earth
水蒸氣是地球上最大的溫室氣氛
The so-called Hu-color equilibrium temperature on the earth is about minus 21 degrees
地球上所謂的胡色平衡溫度大概零下21度
very cold
非常冷啊
The earth is supposed to be cold
地球本來是應該很冷的
But the earth is not that cold
可是地球竟然沒有那麼冷
Why
為什麼
Because the earth's surface releases some water vapor
因為地球地表會釋放一些水蒸氣出來
This water vapor surrounds our planet
這些水蒸氣包圍我們地球
making the earth's surface
使得地球表面上
So increasing the temperature
所以增加了溫度
The average temperature of our earth is about 15 degrees
使得我們地球平均溫度大概15度左右
So from minus 21 degrees to 15 degrees
所以從零下21度增到15度
Added 36 degrees
加了36度
80 to 90 credits for this concentration
這個集中80到90的功勞
It's all crystal
都是水晶氣
not carbon dioxide
不是二氧化碳
Then you must feel very strange
那你心裡一定覺得很奇怪
Otherwise, now everyone is teaching carbon dioxide what is the truth
那不然現在大家教二氧化碳是什麼道理
Because everyone thinks that crystal aura is a state of balance
因為大家認為水晶氣是一種平衡狀態
When there is more crystal gas, it will become a cloud
水晶氣多了以後它會成雲
So go back to the state of crystal air
所以再回到水晶氣的狀態
it just keeps looping
它就是一直循環
So has the crystal energy increased?
所以水晶氣到底有沒有增多
we do not know
我們不知道
Let's say it's balanced
假設說它是平衡
But the carbon dioxide cools down
可是二氧化碳明明涼出來
just keep going up
就是一直往上升
so it's obvious
所以這很顯然
It must have this warming effect
它一定有這個增溫的作用
That's why we now put carbon dioxide
這就是為什麼我們現在把二氧化碳
Considered an important greenhouse base
認為是重要的溫室基地
But if you talk about the real magnitude
但是你如果講真正的幅度來講
Carbon dioxide is not
二氧化碳並不是最大
really the biggest thing
真正最大的事
crystal air
水晶氣
In addition to water vapor, clouds actually have a great stabilizing effect
除了水中氣之外,雲其實也有很大的增穩作用
It's just that clouds are difficult to measure, which is a bit of a headache
只是說雲很難量,這一點比較頭痛一點
OK, so this cloud has a lot of problems
OK,所以這個雲問題很多
Are clouds stabilizing or cooling?
雲到底是增穩還是降溫
Clouds, as we just talked about, are major contributors to the Earth's albedo
雲我們剛才講的,是主要地球反照率的貢獻者
So if it's cloudy, it reflects the light back
所以雲多的話,它會反射光線回去
light is reflected much more of course
光線被反射得多當然
This means that less energy from the sun passes through
這代表太陽能量透過來的少
So in terms of its role, it should cool the ground
所以它以那個角色來講,它應該是使地面降溫才對
But if the ground radiation goes up,
可是地面的輻射如果往上跑的時候
The cloud will absorb him and then reflect it back to him
雲就會把他吸收掉,然後再給他反射回來
So in terms of that role, it also has a stabilizing effect
所以以那種角色來講,它又有增穩的作用
so this is bad, what to do
所以這下很糟糕,怎麼辦
To make matters worse, low clouds are not the same as high clouds
更糟糕的是,低的雲跟高的雲又不一樣
low cloud, it is now common opinion to say
低的雲,它現在一般的意見認為說
low cloud it is mostly
低的雲它主要是
Has a warming and cooling effect
有減暖降溫的作用
Its main function is to slow down the sunlight
它主要的作用是把太陽光緩色回去
It does not have much heat dissipation in this brook
它這個溪熱在散熱不太有
no effect
沒有什麼作用
But high clouds like cirrus clouds
可是高的雲像捲雲
Just saw those cirrus clouds
剛才看了那些捲雲
It does have the effect of steaming and warming
它倒是有蒸暖的作用
If there are many cirrus clouds
如果光光捲雲多的話
it may creek a lot hotter
它可能溪了很多熱
before spreading it back
然後才把它散回來
it dissipates heat by itself
它自己也會散熱
But its heat dissipation is the so-called black body radiation
可是它散熱熱是那種所謂的黑體輻射
It radiates from a black body because its temperature itself is very cold
它這種黑體輻射因為它溫度本身就很冷
So it dissipates very little heat
所以它散熱熱其實很少
So it's generally
所以它總的來講
It has more effect of steaming and warming
它是蒸暖的作用比較多
So now it becomes two to balance
所以現在變成兩個要去平衡
After all, the cooling effect of low clouds is more important
就是到底低雲的降溫作用比較重要
Is it more important for the steaming and warming effect of high clouds?
還是高雲的蒸暖作用比較重要
Let's see which one is more
那就看哪一個多一點
right
對不對
low cloud or high cloud
低雲多還是高雲多
Now the question is how cool is Gao Yun
現在問題是說高雲怎麼涼
This is a big problem
這個問題就很大了
Except for the so-called cirrus clouds that you can see with your eyes
除了你眼睛可以看得到的所謂的捲雲
beyond the high altitude cirrus clouds
高空捲雲之外
It's so hot that there are cirrus clouds that are invisible to the eyes
熱到還有那種所謂眼睛看不到的捲雲
Its eyes can't see the silver roll, not only can't see
它那個眼睛看不到捲銀 不但是看不到
And it's very thick
而且它的厚度還非常厚
Its thickness is sometimes as thick as six or seven kilometers
它的厚度有時候六七公里那麼厚
It's full of ice crystals
裡面都是冰晶
But because of it, the ice crystal will grow smaller
但是因為它那個冰晶會長小
you can't see your eyes can't see
你就看不到 眼睛看不到
So I thought it was not
所以以前認為是沒有
I can’t see it anymore, no, yes
後來再看不得了 不是沒有 是有
So now the question is
所以現在問題就是說
Is that thing real or general?
那個東西到底是真文還是將文
Now everyone will become confused
現在大家要變得搞不懂
So now NASA has another very important
所以現在NASA還有一個很重要的
This mission on climate is
關於氣候方面的這個使命就是
to observe these things
去觀測這些東西
Show me every layer of these clouds
把這些雲的每一層都都給我觀測出來
Then observe clearly
然後觀測清楚
Only when you can truly cleanse people
你才能真正下潔人的時候
What is the role of clouds in the atmospheric environment
雲在大氣環境中到底是扮演
The role of real text or general text
真文還是將文的作用
This thing needs to do this
這個東西有需要做這種
This kind of observation in three-dimensional space can
三度空間的這種觀測才可以
that's a big problem
那這個問題很大
Because satellite observations are roughly one layer
因為衛星觀測大概就是一層
Most of the satellites now have better ones
多半的衛星 現在有比較好一點的
But that observation is still too far off
可是那個觀測還是差得太遠
Observing it from the ground is even more different
地面觀測它更不一樣
There are not many quantities that can have this kind of data
根本就沒有幾個量可以有這種資料
There is no information on the sea
海面上一點資料都沒有
So the question of cloud to climate research
所以雲給氣候的研究的問題
create very, very big problems
產生非常非常大的問題
So why this IPCC
所以為什麼這個IPCC
This body of research climate across the board
這個跨政務監的這種研究氣候的囤體
That is to say, for all radiation factors
就是說對所有的輻射因素裡面
Carbon dioxide warms up, other clouds have something to cool them down
二氧化碳增溫其他雲有降溫的東西
But it turned into a big thing here
可是它化了很大的一個東西在這裡
is its uncertainty
就是它的不確定性
because we have clouds and climates
因為我們對雲還有氣候
Just now these knots also know that there are too few
剛才這些凌結也知道是太少
Lingjie is producing clouds again
凌結又是產生雲
If you have a lot of knots inside
你如果裡面凌結很多
a little cloud will increase
稍微雲會增多
So it does something else that we don't understand at all
所以它又有一些作用我們完全不了解
So it has a lot of uncertainty
所以它有很大的不確定性
so much uncertainty
這麼大的不確定性
So this picture is often seen by many people
所以這一張圖就很多人常常在看
Why is this place often emphasized in its fourth report that
這個地方為什麼它的第四次報告裡面常常強調說
We can only say that this thing can be determined to a certain extent
我們只能說這個東西能夠確定到某個程度
Pretty sure, slightly sure, not sure or something
非常肯定 稍微肯定不太肯定什麼之類的
Why do you use such words?
都用這種話為什麼
Because the cloud represents a great uncertainty
因為雲代表一種很大的不確定性
there are worse nightmares inside
裡面還有更糟糕的噩夢在裡面
There are also clouds in Pingliu City
平流城裡面也有雲
We're not right, Stratocity used to think that Stratocity was very dry
我們說不對啊 平流城以前認為平流城非常乾燥
no cloud possible
不可能有雲
But our recent observations show that Stratocity does have
可是我們最近的觀測是平流城的確有
On a storm you often see
在一個風暴上面你常常看到
Sometimes clouds like chimneys are up there
有時候像煙囪一樣的雲在上面
Someone actually saw it before
以前其實有人看到
but don't know what it is
可是不知道它是什麼東西
Later someone saw it and published it
後來有人看到把它發表出來
But he still doesn't know why
可是他還是不知道什麼原因
It is indeed in Stratocity
它的確是在平流城裡面
because this has been
因為這個已經
This really strong part
這個真壯營的部分
The top of this storm is already at the top of Stratocity
這個風暴的頂已經在平流城的頂了
This so-called chimney-like chimney
這個所謂的煙囪狀的煙囪狀
it's more on top of this cloud
它更在這個雲的頂上
So it's clearly in the bottle layer
所以它很顯然就是在瓶流層裡面
We now know that in terms of radiation
我們現在知道說以輻射來講
If water vapor in this vial layer
這個瓶流層如果水蒸氣的話
Its role in absorbing this infrared
它的吸收這種紅外線的作用
It is nearly 1000 times that in the bottle layer
是它在瓶流層的將近1000倍
So it's very powerful
所以它非常強的作用
It is equivalent to building a very effective quilt in this thermal layer
它等於是在這個對熱層裡蓋了一個非常有效的棉被
Your long-wave radiation can't escape if you want to escape.
你那個長波輻射想要跑出去就跑不掉了
it's there covered
它就在那裡蓋住了
So if there are many of these things
所以這東西如果多的話
Then this positive temperature effect is incredible.
那這個正溫作用是不得了
so this thing knows what's going on
所以這個東西知道什麼回事
We are now gradually understanding
我們現在逐漸有在瞭解
This is the result of our simulation
這是我們的模擬的結果
indeed with that fishing mode
的確用那個漁模式
You can simulate it just like what you see in that satellite
你可以模擬出來就像那個衛星裡面看到一樣
like a chimney cloud
就像一個煙囪的雲一樣
So let's explain
所以我們就瞭解說
In the process of generating a machine cloud
在一個機雲產生的過程中
Due to the effect of these fluctuations
由於這些波動的作用
You can make this water vapor or even moisture
你可以使這水蒸氣或者甚至水分
From the cloud all the way to the bottle layer
從雲裡面一直噴到瓶流層裡面
and then later
然後以後呢
it might stay there
它就可能留在那裡
steam off
蒸化掉
Then leave the air in the water completely at the bottom of the bottle layer
然後把這水中氣完全留在瓶流層的底部
so this time
所以這個時候
Its vibration effect may be very powerful
它的振紋作用可能就很厲害了
so what about this
所以這一點呢
In the current climate model again
又是目前的氣候模式裡面
where little is considered
幾乎沒有考慮到的地方
so here
所以這裡面
Now this problem is very, very much
現在這個問題非常非常多
So this is what we just said
所以這個就是剛才我們講的說
inside the vial layer
在瓶流層裡面
It may have a strong effect of this addition
它可能產生很強的這種加入作用
And the air in the water is in the bottle layer
而且水中氣在瓶流層裡面
it has a long lifespan
它的生命期很長
it may have a lifespan of several years
它可能有幾年的生命期
Then once your life span is so long
那一旦你這個生命期這麼長的話
What do you think about this climate change factor
你對這個氣候改變的這個因素
it can be very big
就可能非常的大
So this is the climate model guy again
所以這個又是氣候模式的人
need attention
所需要注意的
So why this cloud of uncertainty
所以為什麼這個雲的不確定因素
so important
那麼那麼重要
This is one of the important reasons
這是很重要的原因之一
So when the school encounters cloud problems in the future
所以當這個以後學校碰到雲的問題
Its suspicions can be explosive like this
它的懷疑可能是像這樣爆跳如雷的
I can't help it. I don't understand.
沒有辦法了 搞不懂
so angry
氣得好死
Because the uncertainties of the cloud are too great
因為雲的這種不確定因素實在太大了
Except that this cloud has certain roles in the world
除了這個雲在全球裡面有某些角色之外
Will human activities have any impact on the cloud?
人類的活動對雲會不會有什麼影響
there must be
那肯定是有的
The first one is what everyone calls an acid shadow
第一個是大家所說的一個酸影
Human industrial activities produce many such
人類的工業活動產生很多這種
Sulfur dioxide Oxidized eggs
二氧化硫 氧化蛋
Acid Shadow
跟雲作用下來產生酸影
The main source of sulfur dioxide is burning coal and thermal power
二氧化硫主要的來源就是燒煤 火力化電
This oxidized egg reacts with the cloud to produce acid elimination
這個氧化蛋跟雲作用產生消酸
Where does the acid-reducing oxidized egg come from?
消酸的氧化蛋哪裡來
All magnanimous people will have this problem
所有的大度會通通有這個問題
This is when I was about to land from Tokyo
這個是有一次要從東京降落的時候
From the accounting network
從會計網上排的
The entire vicinity of Tokyo is shrouded in the air of the nuclear installation
整個東京附近就是被核設的空氣籠罩住
So there are a lot of oxidation products in it.
所以裡面就是一大堆氧化單的產生物
All of them have this phenomenon inside
全部都有這種現象在裡面
All metropolises as long as the weather is good
所有的大都市 只要天氣好
acid rain
酸雨
Photos taken in 1908
1908年拍的照片
It's been 200 years since it was taken in 1908
1908年拍的時候 它已經經過200年
it's still fine
它還好好的
But after another 60 years
可是再經過60年
unrecognizable
所真正的所謂面目全非
I can't see anything from the face to the nose.
人臉 鼻子什麼全都看不清楚
Standard Acid Rain Effects
標準的酸雨的作用
The second one is that the influence of the moon is Xue Humei
第二個是輪月的影響是薛虎美麗
Everyone should be very clear about this map.
大家對這個地圖應該非常清楚是什麼地方
with tokyo influence
有東京的影響
During the northeast monsoon, a large pile of this kind of smoke is produced in the industrial area upstream of the industrial area
東北季風的時候在工業區上游的工業區產生一大堆這種煙霧
Then they come down here with the northeast monsoon
然後他們隨著東北季風往下來經過這裡
The whole is a long strip
整個就是一長條
Japanese Jiye you can on the satellite map
日語季業你可以在衛星圖上
We are called MODIS
我們叫做MODIS
Seen from satellites that end reliability
終結信度的衛星上面看到
often see this
常常看到這種情況
You can imagine why older
你可以想像為什麼年紀比較大一點
Crash Island and our age
像崩潰島跟我們這種年紀
When we were young, when it was sunny in Taiwan
我們小時候 台灣的晴天的時候
The blue sky is really very blue
藍天真的是非常的藍
It was really blue
那時候真的是藍
Now children may think that the blue sky is also blue now
現在小孩可能認為現在藍天也很藍
I tell you now the blue sky is not blue at all
我告訴你現在藍天一點都不藍
Now the sky is blue, the sky is sunny, and the sky is gray
現在藍天就是晴天天空也是灰白灰白的
not at all blue
一點藍都沒有
Why
為什麼
too clear
太清楚了
Because the neighbor next door generates a lot of
因為隔壁的鄰居產生大量
so there is no way
所以這個沒有辦法
Here's a lot of human influence on this levitation example
這是人類對這個懸浮為例產生的大量影響
look at its different colors
你看看它不同的顏色
It's the smog and the clean sea
就是產生煙霧跟很乾淨的海面
This contrast is too great
這個對比實在太大了
We don't even have that color here
我們這裡連這種顏色都沒有
the color we have here
我們這裡那個顏色
It's almost the picture of this kind of satellite that I often look at
幾乎是我常常看這種衛星的圖
We Taiwanese nurses rarely see such a blue sea color
我們台灣護士很少看到那麼藍的海面顏色
Must be through this more smoky color
一定都透過這種比較煙霧狀的顏色
This is the distribution of small particles of PM2.5 around the world
這個是小粒子的PM2.5在全世界的分布
There is a lot of this kind of fine dust in the desert
沙漠地帶很多這種細小的灰塵
because it's a desert
因為它是沙漠地帶
But eastern China is clearly not a desert
不過中國東部很顯然不是沙漠地帶
But you can also see
不過你也可以看得出來
industrial impact
工業的影響
This is almost now the highest region in the world
這個幾乎現在是全世界最高的地區
most concentrated area
最集中的地區
So the northeast monsoon comes down
所以在東北季風下來
Taiwan is sure to enjoy
台灣就是一定享受到
OK is the Xionghu Weili team
OK 人為雄湖維力隊
already said
已經講了
The first increases the number of condensation nuclei
第一個增加凝結核的數量
If the concentration of water aeration is the same
如果水增氣濃度一樣的話
The size of cloud water droplets will become smaller
雲的水滴的尺度會變小
Cloud particles get smaller
雲的粒子會變小
it will become more stable
它會變得比較穩定
If the cloud strength is stable, it will be less likely to rain
雲力量穩定它就不太會下雨
once it doesn't rain
它一旦不下雨
It is less likely to wash away the paint dust
它就不太會沖刷這個繪塵
So the possibility of air pollution
所以空氣中污染的可能性
higher and higher
都比較越來越高
Then what
然後呢
Because condensation nuclei may dissolve in the water
因為凝結核可能溶解在水裡面
condensation nuclei
凝結核一多
it may be relatively strong water droplets
它可能會比較強的水滴
easier to spill
比較容易溢滴
then we know that means
那我們知道就是說
a highly concentrated droplet
一個高濃度的溶溢滴
it is less accretive
它比較不會增化
dirty water
髒的水
You see usually it's not very accretive
你看通常它不太會增化
Clean water is easy to multiply
乾淨的水很容易就增化
dirty water on the ground
髒的水在地面
Things on the ground last longer
地面的東西比較久一點
the same in the cloud
在雲裡面也是一樣
As long as the cloud is dirty
只要雲比較髒的話
That cloud will last a little longer
那個雲會撐得比較久一點
There are usually more clouds, which increase the albedo
那雲一般多它增加反照率
it lowers the surface temperature
它就會降低表面溫度
seriously pollute the air
嚴重的污染整個空氣
OK but there's a lot more in it
OK 但是裡面還有很多
We have no mention of electrical effects
我們對電影響我們沒有提到
because time is not enough
因為時間實在是不太夠
so many things
所以這麼多的東西
your best bet is
你最好的辦法就是
if you have a way to fly to the sky
你如果有辦法飛到天上
Then look from below
然後從下面看
Now of course we can't fly
現在我們當然沒辦法飛
But someone flew for us
可是有人替我們飛了
This is called the International Space Station
這就是所謂的國際太空站
So this one might take that voice and put it
所以這個可能會把那個聲音把它
Push to
推到
look down
上面往下看
pile of lightning
大堆閃電
OK, thank you all for today
OK 好 今天謝謝大家
Thank you Jin Tai for the speech this last game last this
謝謝金台的演講這個最後遊戲最後這個
Very good at shooting outer space to see the earth
很能拍外太空看地球
ok we have 10 minutes to start
好 我們開始還有10分鐘
do we have any questions please
我們請大家有問題了嗎
consult
請教
ask the professor
請教教授
Just now the professor mentioned many kinds of
剛剛教授有提到很多種類的
For example, Jiyin, Jianying, and Chen Jiyin
比如說基隱、檢營還有陳基隱
Please teach me the number sound of tornado
請教教授龍捲風的數音
what type of sound thanks
哪一類型的音 謝謝
he has nothing to do with either
他跟這兩個都沒有關係
He said something completely different
他有說完全另外一種
You are sounding like the fluctuating sound I mentioned just now
你在像剛才我提的波動音
Also not included in the earliest mentioned
也沒有包含在最早提的這種
He is another way of classifying
他又是另外一種分類的辦法
So Long Jianfeng, rolled up, is that a cloud?
所以龍檢風那個捲起來那個是不是雲
that's cloud
那是雲
that cloud
那那個雲
That cloud is not a cloud
那雲不是算雲
Clouds are just about light
雲那個只是光線的關係
So the one that was rolled up by the wind of dragon inspection
所以那個龍檢風捲起來的那個
That name is Lu Douyun
那個名字叫露斗雲
Lu Douyun
露斗雲
He looks like Ludo
他就像露斗一樣的形象
Gradually
漸漸的
Thanks
謝謝
good
好
Director Wang
王主任
Excuse me
請問一下
That is, the continental climate will obviously
就是大陸的氣候很明顯會
It is the polluted road that will obviously pollute Taiwan
就是污染路很明顯會污染到台灣
That's our main polluting line
那但是我們最主要污染行
That is to say, the northeast monsoon
就是說都是東北季風
The Northeast is not a continent
那東北並不是大陸
The Northeast comes from Japan and the Pacific Ocean.
東北是從日本還有太平洋那個方向過來的
So why the mainland
所以為什麼大陸的
going in such a strange direction
會經過這樣的一個很奇怪的方向
blow to Taiwan
吹到台灣來
The northeast monsoon is only because
東北季風只是因為
to us is northeast
到我們這裡是東北
But from the original place, I don’t think it’s the Northeast
可是從原地來不覺得是東北
that domineering transfer
那個霸氣的轉移
In fact, it is mostly a circular motion.
其實多半都是一種圓形的運動
a little more
比較多一點
it won't say from there
它不會說從那邊
It's all the way from the northeast
就是東北一直過來
not like this
不是這樣子
so this situation
所以這種情況
It's like bypassing Japan and coming back.
就等於繞過日本再過來
Bypass Japan, South Korea and come again
繞過日本、韓國再過來
so keep coming
所以一直在過來
Another little problem is that
那另外一個小問題就是說
Just mentioned that water vapor is the main greenhouse gas
剛剛講到水蒸氣是最主要的溫室氣體
But crocodile carbon is man-made
但是鱷陽化碳是人為造成
a greenhouse gas that has been increasing
一直在增加的一個溫室氣體
After the crocodile carbon dioxide increases
那鱷陽化碳增加以後
until the temperature increases
是為止溫度增高
Does the increase in temperature increase the stability of the earth's water vapor?
那溫度增高是不是就把地球的水蒸氣的平穩往上抬
After that lift up
那往上抬以後
The temperature increased further
那溫度又更進一步的提高
Will it have such a vicious effect?
是不是會有這種惡性的作用呢?
this has a possibility
這個有一個可能
not completely impossible
不是完全不可能
But now when reading this article
但是目前在看完這篇文章的時候
On a yearly scale
以一年的尺度來講
more water vapor
水蒸氣一多
Rainfall will also increase
雨量也會增多
because of the source of moisture
因為水氣的來源
The source of that rain is water vapor
那個雨的來源就是水蒸氣
So you make water vapor and rain increase
所以你叫水蒸氣都雨也增多
So on a yearly basis
所以以一年的尺度來講
Take it easy
照理一講
These two should balance each other
這兩個應該互相平衡
So the annual flower increase and the annual precipitation
所以一年的增花量跟一年的降水量
The two should just cancel out
兩個應該是剛好抵消掉
So for the whole year
所以整年來講
That is, on average, the amount of air in water in your earth
就是平均來講你地球裡面的水中氣量
indeed will increase
的確是會增多
But the rainfall will also increase
但是降雨量也會增多
But what you just asked probably meant
但是你剛才問的大概就是說
The increased air volume in the water
那這樣增多的水中氣量
Will it increase the temperature inside the earth?
會不會增加地球裡面的溫度也會增高
the answer is yes
那答案就是會的
And the so-called warming
而且目前所謂的增暖
It is mentioned in the mode that this calculation is included in it.
模式裡面提到都有把這個計算在裡面
I've already factored in this warming up.
都已經把這個增暖也算進去了
good
好
is there any problem
還有沒有什麼問題
professor
教授
Just that video, the last video
剛剛那個影片最後這一段影片
It's like burning the physiology
好像火燒生理那個
what does that mean
那個是代表什麼
There are not many, but the one that seems to be on fire
沒有就很多好像火在燒的那個
you say green red
你說綠色紅色
red a lot like
紅色很多很多像
The one that burns like magma
火燒像岩漿那個
That's actually in space
那個其實在太空裡面
That's called Aurora
那個叫做極光
like the aurora borealis
像北極極光嗎
Are there so many auroras?
極光有那麼多嗎
why is it light
它為什麼是燈光
the red one all over the place
整個遍布的紅色那個
fixed bit by bit
固定的一點一點
very many
很多很多
That is the night in the city
那個是都市裡面的晚上
of course you see a little
當然你看到一點
you don't really see a light
你不是真的看到一個燈
Lights across the metropolitan area
整個都市區的亮光
Maybe it's in space
大概它這個太空上
waste time
廢過去的時候
The whole, for example, the whole of Taipei City
整個譬如說整個台北市
just see a little
就看到一點
it's a light like this
就是一個亮光這樣
all covered
全部都布滿了
are all cities
都是都市
Thanks
謝謝
we just want to ask
我們就想請問一下
you just mentioned
您剛有提到就是
We currently lack global
我們現在非常缺乏全球的
3D Cloud Observation
3D雲的觀測
then i'm curious
那我很好奇就是
is there any possibility
有沒有怎麼樣的可能性
can proceed
可以進行
because we usually now see
因為我們通常現在看到
just look up from the ground
就從地面往上看
looking down from the sky
跟從高空往下看的
just to see the flickering
就是要看到閃低的
is there any possibility
有沒有什麼樣的可能性
Thanks
謝謝
And the possibility is that
而可能性就是說
It's better to have a lot of these tactics
要最好佈滿很多這種策戰
One of the current satellites is
目前的衛星有一種是
a cloud radar
一種叫做雲雷達
That cloud moon called Clausian
那個叫做Clausian的雲衛星
It is different from ordinary satellites
它就跟一般衛星比較不一樣
Ordinary satellites are cloud satellites that use visible photosynthesis
一般衛星就是用可見光合的雲衛星
look
看
But what you see is a plane equal to this
但是你看到是一個等於這個平面
just one layer
一層這樣而已
This new relatively new relic
這種新的比較新的遺跡
it can penetrate
它可以穿透
Then in theory it could see several layers
然後在理論上它可以看到好幾層
The current satellite
目前這種衛星
it is not a geostationary satellite
它並不是一種同步衛星
If geostationary satellite
如果同步衛星
It says it can be 24 hours a day
它就說可以一天24小時
all have been watching
全部都一直在看
At present, this kind of satellite is only a kind of orbiting satellite
現在目前這種只是一種繞級的衛星
So it just selects
所以它只是選擇
just for a certain period of time
某一個時段看而已
so the data
所以資料
incomplete is
不完整就是
but there is a possibility in the future
但是將來有可能性
If we say that the future technology is so high that
假如說將來科技高到
Pompeo also has such a thing
蓬佩奧會心也有這種玩意
There is also this radar
也有這種雷達
There is also this cloud radar
也有這種雲雷達
From such a high altitude of tens of thousands of kilometers
可以從那麼高的幾萬公里的高空
penetrate the ground and make observations
透到地面然後做觀測
that's possible
那就有可能
This kind of global 3D observation is possible
可以進行這種全球3D的觀測
Professor OK Wang
OK 王教授
thank you for a very good presentation
謝謝你非常精彩的演講
I have a question
我有一個問題
You mean the water and water vapor on the earth
你就是說地球上的水跟水蒸氣
Is it constant
是不是constant
won't it disappear into space
它不會消失到太空裡面去嗎
Yes
會啊
if so far
如果到目前為止
Disappeared because no one observed
為沒有人觀測到消失掉就是
So since no one observed
所以因為沒有人觀測到
We assume it is always
我們假定它是一直在
always balanced
一直平衡
so many things are said
所以很多東西是說
Let's just say we haven't seen evidence to the contrary
我們只能說我們沒有看到相反的證據
That is to say, we don't know for sure
就是說目前我們不知道說不定
The water in the earth is increasing
地球裡面的水是有在增加的
Maybe there is a lot of water coming in from outer space, we don't know
說不定外太空有很多水跑進來我們也不知道
So do you think there is such a possibility?
那你說有沒有這種可能呢
Of course it's possible
當然有可能啊
It's just that we have nothing to do with it
只是我們沒有關係到而已
Directly connected to the earth, there is another promise
直系上地球另外有一個答應
That's what we call Jiawan
就是我們說甲丸
After oxidation, the pill will produce water
甲丸氧化以後會產生水
That's really putting it together
那的確在拼溜成裡面
A lot of steamed juice is due to the oxidation of Jiawan
很多水蒸汁是因為甲丸氧化以後
The generated water vapor is over there
產生的水氣在那邊
So now if the ground is like
所以現在如果地面像
If more and more such pills are released underground,
地底下如果越來越多這種甲丸釋放出來以後
after it is oxidized
它經過氧化以後
it produces oxidized water
它會產生氧化的水
likely to increase
有可能增加
It's also possible that this is another possible measure
這也有可能這是另外一個可能的措施
ok last question
好最後一個問題
ask teacher wang
請教王老師
you just mentioned that there are
你剛才提到有
Tiny particles with negative subscale sizes cannot be sucked down by rainwater
有負分尺度尺寸的微小粒子沒辦法被雨水吸下來
If so, will there be more and more pollutants in the air?
那這樣的話大氣人中這些污染物會不會越來越多
ah
啊
it gets to a point where it might reach a certain balance
它到某一個地步它可能會達到某一種平衡
not always
不會一直
take that sentence back in half
這句話要收回一半
If humans do not go too far
假如人類沒有太過分的
if humans go too far
人類如果太過分的話
Then I think it will keep increasing
那我想是會一直增加
Because it will exceed the nature of this
因為它會超過大自然這種
This efficiency in removing pollution from the air
清除空氣中污染的這種效率
Once you exceed this limit
你一旦超過這種極限的話
it keeps increasing
它會一直增加
This is the so-called wrong away
這是所謂的wrong away
just follow
就跟在
we all know why
大家知道為什麼
elaborate why make me hot
精心為什麼讓我熱
Because its soup is called wrong away
因為它的湯叫wrong away
it can't be balanced
它沒有辦法打到平衡
A water vapor it is the same as the earth
一個水蒸氣它跟地球一樣
Its water vapor also flowed from the ground
它水蒸氣當初也從地面
it pops out of the ground
它的地底下冒出來
we are tough here
我們這裡是硬氣
then we will take business
然後我們會接生意
because it is too close to the sun
那邊因為太靠近太陽
it's too hot
它太熱了
so it's been water vapor
所以它一直是水蒸氣
it broke down shortly after
不久以後它分解掉了
So its water vapor decomposes
所以它那個水蒸氣分解掉了
so it's not in its atmosphere
所以它沒有在它的大氣裡面
So that elaborate atmosphere
所以那個精心的大氣
That's hundreds of times the weight of the earth
就是地球幾百倍的重
Because its air-conditioning is not like ours running into the sea
因為它的冷氣不像我們通到跑到海裡面去
no , not gas
就沒有,不是氣體
it's always been inside its origin
它都一直在它發起裡面
So this great potential
所以這個大界勢
There's no way it can go back, there's no way it can be balanced
它沒有辦法回到,沒有辦法達到平衡
Then what I just said at this time
那我剛才講的這個時候
If human beings are always in the air
人類如果一直在空氣裡面一直
send in this
送進這種
so many particles
這麼多的微粒的話
someday
那總有一天
The forces of nature cannot remove
大自然的力量沒有辦法清除
this time is
這個時候就是
It is not stipulated, this is point on no return
就是不規定,這是point on no return
it's possible
這有可能
OK, let's thank Director Wang again
好,那我們再一次謝謝王主任
thank you all
謝謝大家